<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A caveat against covetousness occasioned by some scandalous and pernicious fruit of it, in one amongst us, whose heart went after it / written for admonition to others, by Charles Phelpes.</title>
            <author>Phelpes, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 221 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54652</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13348</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12033644</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12033644</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52825</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54652)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52825)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 873:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A caveat against covetousness occasioned by some scandalous and pernicious fruit of it, in one amongst us, whose heart went after it / written for admonition to others, by Charles Phelpes.</title>
                  <author>Phelpes, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Avarice.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52825:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52825:1"/>
            <p>A CAVEAT AGAINST Covetouſneſs, OCCASIONED By ſome ſcandalous and pernicious Fruit of it, in one amongſt us, whoſe heart went after it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written for Admonition to others,</hi> BY CHARLES PHELPES.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Tim. 6. 9, 10.</bibl>
But they that will be rich fall into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a ſnare, and many fooliſh, and hurtful luſts, which drown men in deſtruction and perdition; For the love of Money is the root of all evil, which while ſome coveted after, they have erred from the faith, and pierced themſelves thorow with many ſorrows.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Joh. 8. 7.</bibl>
He that is without ſin among you, let him firſt caſt a ſtone at her.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year 1668.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:52825:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52825:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE READER In General,</hi> And eſpecially to ſuch as have heard the Father, and been taught by him as the truth is in Jeſus, and know that he is indeed the Chriſt, the Savior of the World.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He enſuing Treatiſe was at firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended onely for mine own private uſe, and the helpfulneſs of ſuch as by the providence of God are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to me to bring up in the Nurture and Admonition of the Lord; and though I was urged by the perſwaſion of ſome to make it publique, yet it prevailed not with me, conſidering mine own great weakneſs, and unmeetneſs, and that another had intended, if God preſerved him, and gave op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb facs="tcp:52825:3"/>
to have a blow at this root of all evil, to wit, <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> who was more abundantly ſitted of God, and prepared to every good word, and work, and faithful in the Lord; But now I conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and was willing to do that which formerly I knew not how to think of; The Reaſons which ſwayed me at laſt hereto, were</p>
            <p>1. And principally, becauſe the Perſon before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to, who, in the latter end of the Preface to his Treatiſe, Entituled, <hi>Fornication condemned,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified his intention to diſcover the ſinfulneſs of this Sin, I mean, my deareſt Brother, and moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Helper in the Lord, <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> Junior, was removed and taken from the earth, and died in the Lord, before he had accompliſhed, or begun to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh what (as to this particular) was upon his heart: His dayes are paſt, his purpoſes broken off, even the thoughts of his heart, as <hi>Job</hi> 17. 11. he reſts from his labours, and his works follow him, and ſhall be remembred and recompenſed in the reſurrection of the Juſt; For the iniquity of our Covetouſneſs God was wroth, and ſmote us, in taking away that merciful man, that man of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and godlineſs from amongſt us. See and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 57. 1. with Verſe 17. To him to live was Chriſt, and to die gain, and it is far better with him that he is departed, and is with Chriſt, than to have continued longer in the fleſh; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs to have abidden in the fleſh had been more needful for us that our rejoycing might have been more abundant in Chriſt Jeſus, and this mercy we might have enjoyed had our Converſation been as
<pb facs="tcp:52825:3"/>
becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt, as <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 21-27. He might have been reſtored to us again, had our Converſation been without Covetouſneſs. See <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 5. 19. Our wayes, and our doings have procured this ſevere teſtimony of diſpleaſure to our ſelves, this is our wickedneſs, becauſe it is bitter, it reacheth even to the very heart; My bowels, my bowels, I am pained at my very heart, my heart maketh a noiſe in me, I cannot hold my peace, becauſe thou haſt heard, O my Soul (in this ſtroke) the ſound of the Trumpet, the Alarm of War. Compare <hi>Jer.</hi> 4. 18-21. with Chapter 6. 13-15. Wo unto us that we have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; that though we have ſitten before God as his people, and heard his words, (yea have been hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, made a trade of it) and this his ſervant hath been unto us as a very lovely Song of one that hath a pleaſant Voice, and could play well on an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for we heard his words, yet have not done them, our heart hath not been eſtranged from its luſt, but hath gone after its Covetouſneſs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God hath begun to make us deſolate, and to know (by his deprivation) that a Prophet hath been amongſt us. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 29-33. He is now taken from the evil, and there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wiſdom in the grave, where he is, and whither we are going; He hath no more a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ever in any thing that is done under the Sun, nor ſhall he return to perfect any thing left undone. Now then that I might execute the Will of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed (though moſt unworthy) I have done what I have done.</p>
            <p>2. Upon the former account, and in concurrence
<pb facs="tcp:52825:4"/>
with him that is now removed, I have committed this to publick view, becauſe I judge that the evil herein warned of, is not onely very hurtful and pernicious in it ſelf, and provoking to the eyes of Gods glory, (as I have endeavored to demonſtrate) but alſo (as I fear) very much enclined to, and entertained, not onely by ſuch as have a form of godlineſs upon them, and deny the power thereof, but by ſuch alſo as have known, and believed the love that God hath manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to us, in ſending his Son to be the Savior of the World; Oh that their hearts were not too generally inclined to it, yea that this ſpot, which is not the ſpot of Gods children, were not in its fruits ſo eaſily diſcernable upon them, that it may be found without ſecret ſearch, ſo as that they teach the wicked ones their ways, and ſtrengthen the hands of evil doers. I have a little obſerved of late, and ſeen ſomewhat of it (if I be not deceived, Oh that I may be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in it) ſome grievous, and ſadning evidences of it in Gods pleaſant plant; not only in the great miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of one, which occaſioned the conſidering this place of Scripture, but in others alſo; in ſome, lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in ſtead of taking wrong, and ſuffering themſelves to be defrauded, to do wrong, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud, and that their brethren, and others alſo, and that before the unbelievers, even in their view and preſence, cauſing them to open their mouthes wide againſt the Name of God, and his Doctrine, and ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and offending the weak, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 1-9. In others, hindring them from ſuch a promoting the things of Chriſt, and endeavoring the good of their brethren, in their word, as their hearts have been ſet for, and inclined unto, becauſe their expectations have not
<pb facs="tcp:52825:4"/>
been anſwered in the conveniences, and accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the things of this preſent world; In others, in ſhutting up the bowels of their compaſſions when opened, and not remembring to ſhew mercy, but even adding ſorrow to ſorrow, and increaſing affliction to the afflicted, <hi>Pſal. 109. 16. Job</hi> 6. 14-27. and 24. 21. In others, intangling them ſo with the affairs of this life, that they cannot wait upon the Lord with his people without diſtraction, and ſo not pleaſe him who hath choſen them to be ſoldiers, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 3, 4. I might add more, and have ſpoken more particularly, but that I love not, on this ſubject, to ſpeak ſo openly; <hi>Oh tell it not in</hi> Gath, <hi>publiſh it not in the ſtreets of</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kelon, <hi>leſt the daughters of the Philiſtines rejoyce;</hi> Now to this end that I may be ſome way inſtrumental to to the awakening my ſelf and others, to ſearch, and try our hearts and ways, even to ſearch them as with a candle in the light of Gods teſtimony, diligently and narrowly to ſearch into them, that we may, if this iniquity be in our hearts and hands, put it away; I have therefore been willing to become a fool, Oh that I could truly ſay, for Chriſts ſake.</p>
            <p>3. Becauſe (as the conſequent of the former) I am even afraid, leſt Gods judgements ſhould be further poured forth upon us, even ſuch, and of ſuch a nature, as in which he will turn the Songs of the Temple into howlings, and ſend a famine of hearing the words of the Lord, (as is after ſaid) I am perſwaded this iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty retained and ſerved, and the fruit thereof, in ſaying to thoſe that propheſie, <hi>Propheſie not to us right things, ſpeak ſmooth things,</hi> &amp;c. hath already provoked God to make breaches amongſt us, and to order it in his
<pb facs="tcp:52825:5"/>
providences, that ſome of theſe faithful ones ſhall no more propheſie, that others ſhall not take ſhame: and it ſeems to me, as if God were ſtill threatning to take away his tabernacle, as of a Garden, and to deſtroy his places of the aſſembly; for the iniquity of our co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs he is ſtill hiding himſelf, and is wroth, <hi>Micah</hi> 2. 2. 6-11. Oh that we may conſider it, ſo as to flee it, before the decree bring forth, and the day paſs as the chaff, that yet he may turn away his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and comfort us according to the days wherein he hath afflicted us; Or however we may be hid in the day of the Lords anger, and he may be a light to us when we ſit in darkneſs.</p>
            <p>As to my own weakneſs, I acknowledge that the ſhame of my face doth cover me, and I have cauſe to cry out, My leanneſs, my leanneſs; but yet there is mercy and grace with him to whom I ſhould ſtudy to ſhew my ſelf approved; it ſhould be a ſmall thing with me to be judged of men, or of mans day; its not he whom man commends, is therefore approved, and no matter though men curſe, if God bleſs; Oh that I may have to do with him with whom is forgiveneſs, that he may be feared; and that he would pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and healing whatſoever he ſees amiſs in me, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper this work, is the deſire of him who is</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April 30. 1668.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>The moſt unworthy of the leaſt of Gods mercies, and unskilful in the word of his righteouſneſs,
Charles Phelpes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52825:5"/>
            <head>A Caveat againſt Covetouſneſs.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>LUKE 12. 15.</bibl>
And he ſaid unto them, Take beed and beware of Covetouſneſs: For a mans life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hile our Savior in the foregoing part of the Chapter, was (as we may ſee) inſtructing, and encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his diſciples, not to be aſhamed of the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Lord, but to be partakers of the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Goſpel, according to the power of God, as 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 7, 8. One of the company ſaid unto him, <hi>Maſter, ſpeak to my Brother that he divide the inheritance with me.</hi> Verſ. 13. It ſeemes the perſon thus ſpeaking had ſome good eſteem of our Savior, by the Title he gives him, and matter he commits to him; To which requeſt our Savior anſwers.</p>
            <p>1. Particularly to the man himſelf: And he ſaid unto him; <hi>Man, who made me a Judge, or a divider over you?</hi> He would not own, or exerciſe any ſuch authority as he was a Peace-preacher, and while in a mortal body; he would not take upon him to divide the difference, or determine what appertain'd to one, or to the other, though requeſted by one party; For his Kingdom was not of this world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 18 36. Nor did he ſeek for, nor would accept of any worldly greatneſs, while here; Yea when they would have come by force, and have made him king, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted again into a mountain alone, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 15. and inſtructed his diſciples that they ſhould not ſeek for ſuch worldly greatneſs, as the Kings of the earth may lawfully have, and exerciſe. <hi>Math.</hi> 20. 25, 26. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 24. 26. How unlike to our Savior is he that pretends to be his Vicar, and would be accounted the Head of the Church on earth, who not only judges of private matters when deſired by one party, and divides to others equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52825:6"/>
their rights; but converts the revenues of others to himſelf, depoſes Kings, and acquits their<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Subjects of their obedience to them, and diſpoſes their kingdoms to others; Yea and cauſes their lives to be taken away, and ſo exalts himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhip't. And how unſutable to the inſtructions of our Savior to his diſciples, is the exerciſe of the Synagogue of Satan, the Mother of harlots, and her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; who inflict mulcts, and outward puniſhments on thoſe that tranſgreſs their law, and are more ſtrict in puniſhing the breach of them, then of his, who is the onely head, and husband of his body the Church.</p>
            <p>2. Our Savior gives anſwer to this mans deſire more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and for inſtruction to others in this 15. verſe, <hi>And he ſaid unto them,</hi> &amp;c. And in this he includes his diſciples as directly ſpoken to, or however ſpeaks in their hearing, and that for their admonition alſo.</p>
            <p>From the occaſion of the words we may note,</p>
            <p>1. In that this man now makes this requeſt to our Savior, it may teach us; That while men ſit before Chriſt as his people, and are among thoſe that hear his word, yet their heart may be far removed from him, and from his teachings. <hi>Iſay.</hi> 29. 13. it may be wandring after it's covetouſneſs. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 31. 33. While the outward man is preſented before the Lord, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a man profeſſedly waits upon him; Yet the heart, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire may be ſet upon, and wandring after other things, it may be led away with divers luſts from the mindfulneſs of what is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared; and thereby advantage is given to Satan to ſteal away the word of the Lord; Yea he now eſpecially watches for ſuch an advantage, and is very buſy that he may take away that which was ſown in the heart, leſt they ſhould believe, and be ſaved; For the Goſpel is the word of faith, which would, were it retained, worke faith, and ſo ſave them; <hi>faith cometh by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and bearing of the word of God,</hi> Luk. 8. 12. Great need have we therefore to take heed how we hear; to keep our hearts with all keeping, when ſuch a price is put into our hands, leſt what we have heard ſlip away, or be taken from us.</p>
            <p>2. In that this man adds this deſire after thoſe inſtructions, and admonitions given by our Savior to his diſciples, we may learn; That ſuch is the deceitfulneſs of that ſin that dwelleth in us, that it will lead us to pervert what is right, and ſo it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52825:6"/>
unprofitable to us; It appeares that this perſon was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced by our Saviors diſcourſe, that he was a good, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right man, and one to whom he might commit his matters in this particular, and from whom he might expect what was juſt, and equal, and therefore he thus requeſts, <hi>Maſter ſpeak to my Brother.</hi> This he would not have committed to every one; but perceiving he ſpake the words of truth, and ſoberneſs (though not enough ſetting his heart thereto) he purſues his own evil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, under pretence of liking, and eſteeming our Savior, and owning himſelf as his diſciple; Thus alſo thoſe men who have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeen our Saviors Miracle of the loaves, and were thereby convinced, and confeſſed that he was of a truth that Prophet that ſhould come into the world; yet perverting what was right, in ſtead of receiving the law from his mouth, they were ſeeking meat that periſheth, and therefore would have taken him by force, and made him King; that ſo having ſuch a mighty one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, they might have been delivered from their enemies, and injoyed outward peace, fulneſs, and proſperity, and been the head of the nations round about them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 14. 15. See al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 24-27. Even ſo at this time, as it was then ſo it is now: many that are in ſome meaſure convinced of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and truth of the glorious Goſpel, and have ſome eſteem of his diſciples who walk in Chriſt as they have received him, may yet carry on a ſelfiſh deſign; they may, while they hear Chriſt's words, and frequent the aſſemblies of his people, ſeek meat for their luſts, and be purſuing ſome by-end of their own.</p>
            <p>3. In that the man thus vents forth his covetous deſire, after our Savior had thus ſpoken to his diſciples, it may admoniſh us, not to condemn the Goſpel, or declarers of it, becauſe ſtill the heart of thoſe that hear are inclin'd to covetouſneſs; For Chriſt may labor in vain, and ſpend his ſtrength for nought, and in vain, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 4. 5. And ſo may his ſervants alſo do, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 11. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 16. How many were there that heard our Savior, before he was delivered into the hands of men (yea and many might hear him gladly) who yet received not his grace, or received it in vain, and therefore they joyn'd with thoſe that apprehended him, <hi>Math.</hi> 26. 55. This is an evil way, to condemn the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Chriſt, or his diſciples, becauſe of the miſcarriages of thoſe that hear it, or come amongſt them; and walking herein, men
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52825:7"/>
condemn the generation of the juſt; yea and Chriſt himſelf, and his Apoſtles: nor is this a good way to judge of doctrines, <hi>viz.</hi> by the demeanours of thoſe that hear them, but to bring all to the light, to the Law, and to the Teſtimony, 1 <hi>Joh. 4. 1-3. 6. Iſa.</hi> 8. 20. Thoſe that hear the inſtructions that cauſe to erre from the words of knowledge, may have a form of godlineſs upon them, they may appear righteous before men, as the Phariſees new, and old, and yet the leaven and doctrine they imbrace be hypocriſie; And on the other hand there may be many tranſgreſſions found with thoſe that hear the Goſpel, and yet it is a doctrine accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to godlineſs; Yea there may be great miſcarriages found with ſuch as have formerly obeyed from the heart the form of doctrine delivered to them, when the things they have heard have been let ſlip, and yet ſtill the Goſpel is the Goſpel of God, preached ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his commandment; giving a faithful diſcovery of him in Chriſt, and leading to him; and which he will own, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve from this generation for ever: And if while we ſeek to be juſtified by Chriſt, through faith in his blood, without the works of the law, we our ſelves are found ſinners, is Chriſt therefore the Miniſter of ſin? God forbid, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 17. Or is his Goſpel a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of unrighteouſneſs, and ungodlineſs, becauſe thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, believe it in vain? No: Far be it from us that we ſhould blame it. And yet this is the way, and manner of the world, yea and of the ſaints of the world alſo, to lay the fault upon the Goſpel of the grace of God, as preached in the words that the Holy Ghoſt hath taught, if any of thoſe that hear it turn aſide to crooked pathes, as if it were a doctrine of licentiouſneſs, and opened a gap to all profaneneſs and wickedneſs; ſuch reproaches (it may ſeem) were caſt upon it, as preacht by the Apoſtles, as if men might continue in ſin, either becauſe grace had abounded, or that grace might abound, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 5-8. &amp; 6. 12. Though yet there is no doctrine doth ſo much ſhew the vileneſs of our ſins, and the vanity of all idols, as this, in the faithful declaration of it; This ſhews the odious and provoking nature of our natural vileneſs, and filthineſs, and the abominableneſs of continuing therein af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grace vouchſafed, and the neceſſity of our being waſhed, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord, in witneſſing of Chriſt, and ſhewing that there was no other way to purge ſin away from before the preſence of God, then by the abaſement of the Son of God; he muſt needs have ſuffered, and be raiſed again, or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52825:7"/>
otherwiſe we could not be brought back to God, nor could there have been any fountain opened for our waſhing, but at this dear Coſt, and that his end in giving himſelf for us was, that he might deliver us from this preſent evil world according to the will of God, and our Father. Oh how ſhall they that are dead to ſin (this way) live any longer therein; know ye not that ſo many of us as were Baptized into Chriſt (waſhed into union and fellowſhip with him) were baptized into his death (into the knowledge and acknowledgment of his death, in which we ſee the greatneſs of his ſufferings, that he might take away our ſins, and become a fountain thorow his blood for our waſhing, and cleanſing, <hi>Rom. 6. 2. 3. 1 Pet. 4. 1-3. Rom.</hi> 8. 3. 4.) And yet mean time, they that reproach this worthy name, as if it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged men to continue in ſin; and eſpecially ſuch as deny the grace of God in Chriſt to Manward, theſe new Phariſees, they overlook the direct fruit of their damnable hereſies, in which they deny, and teach men to deny the Lord that bought them; I mean thoſe Doctrines in which they teach that Chriſt dyed not for all, nor by the grace of God taſted death for every man; but onely for ſome elect ones (as they ſay) who ſhall certainly be ſaved in concluſion, and be overcome by an irreſiſtable pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and as for the reſt they are reprobated, or at leaſt paſt by, ſo as there is no true, and ſaving grace vouchſafed to them, and therefore they muſt in the iſſue neceſſarily periſh. Doe not theſe apprehenſions received, and heartily digeſted, lead men thus to reaſon? If I be elected, or of that elect number for whom Chriſt dyed, I ſhall infallibly be ſaved, and brought in by an irreſiſtible power, and till then I cannot come in, and therefore till then I had as good walk according to the ſight of mine eyes, and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of mine heart, I ſhall have life in concluſion; And if not, if I be reprobated, or paſt by, how then can I live? ſurely this is the evil fruit of that root of rotteneſs; And yet as it was with the Phariſees of old, who charged Chriſt with being a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, and what he ſaid with blaſphemy, while they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were indeed ſuch, and guilty thereof; ſo it is now with theſe new ones; they fault the Goſpel of Chriſt, as preached by him, and the Apoſtles, as that which gives incouragement to walk after the fleſh, whilſt, in truth that is the iſſue of their falſe doctrines; this way of the old Phariſees was their folly, and yet their poſterity, the new ones, approve their ſayings; ſuch are
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52825:8"/>
to be pittyed, and prayed for, that their eyes may be opened; for many of them have a zeal of God, but not according to knowledg, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 1, 2, 3. But this is their manner, when ſuch as are hearers of the Goſpel miſcarry: and woe to the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of offences, it's a great judgment to them, when God permits, and orders ſuch ſtumbling blocks before a people, and the Father, and the Sons fall together upon them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6. 21. But though <hi>Iſrael</hi> thus play the harlot, let not <hi>Judah</hi> offend, let them not have low thoughts of the Teſtimony of Jeſus, becauſe there are ſuch ſpots found on ſome that joyn with them, as are not the ſpots of his people; but rather love his law more abund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly, by how much the more others make it void, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it to purpoſe, that they may give none occaſion of offence, <hi>but that men ſeeing their good works, may gloriſy their Father which is in Heaven,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 32. Math. 5. 14. 16. 1 Pet. 2. 11-18. and 3. 16.</p>
            <p>4. In that our Savior gives this admonition not to the man onely who made this requeſt, but to others alſo, we may learn; That when miſcarriages are found with one that heares the word, there is occaſion given to warn others alſo, and that all of us ſhould (in ſtead of judging the law of liberty) take warning, and beware of that evil root which brought forth ſuch pernicious fruit in one amongſt us; Thus our Savior by occaſion of the young mans departure from him, as the iſſue of his Covetouſneſs admoniſhes his diſciples, <hi>Mark.</hi> 10. 17-24. ſee alſo <hi>Math.</hi> 16. 22-27. Oh let us ſo couſider the tranſgreſſions of others as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive inſtruction, that we may fear, and do no more ſo preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuouſly. The fall, of Gods people in former times are therefore recorded, not that we ſhould imitate them, or boaſt againſt them, as if our mountain were ſo ſtrong ſetled that we could never be moved, but for our admonition, leaſt we fall after the ſame example of unbelief, <hi>Rom. 11. 18-22. 1 Cor.</hi> 9. 27. and 10. 1-12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 1-11. Be we not high-minded, but fear; For we have ſin alſo dwelling in us, and have ſinned, and if we have been preſerved from ſuch groſs evils as others have been pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with, 'tis by grace we are ſaved, and that excludes boaſting and high-mindedneſs every where; And let us be warned on fight of others evils to beware of that which hath occaſion'd their wandrings, for otherwiſe our evils will be aggravated if when we ſee the falls of others, and the bitter fruit thereof, we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52825:8"/>
not our ways, ſo as to turn our feet to his teſtinonies, <hi>Jer. 3. 7-11. Zeph.</hi> 3. 6-7.</p>
            <p>5. In that our Savior on this occaſion ſo largly inſtructs, and admoniſhes this man and his diſciples, &amp;c. it ſhews that he knows how to bring good out of evil, to cauſe the wrath of man to praiſe him, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76. 10. And to make the miſcarriage of thoſe that hear him of bleſſed uſefulneſs to themſelves, &amp; others; This is not the fruit of their wandring, but of his graciouſneſs to man, and more abundant kindneſs, and pity to his little ones, (who after taſtes of his graciouſneſs have back-ſlidden) while he is waiting upon them, that he may be gracious to them; He needed not this mans venting forth his covetous inclination to the occaſioning theſe Inſtructions, for he knew before what was in his heart, but he takes occaſion thereby to magnifie the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and cordialneſs of his love; even as in our firſt departure from God in <hi>Adam,</hi> he took occaſion to ſhew forth his grace to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward us, ſo as that where ſin abounded, grace abounded much more, ſo he doth ſtill, while called to day; he doth permit men ſometimes to fall, when they have hardned their hearts againſt the reproofs of Inſtruction, and to reap ſomewhat of the fruit of their former ſtiff-neckedneſs, that they may ſee what an evil and bitter thing it is to forſake him; and yet brings light out of darkneſs, and is graciouſly creating the fruit of his lips, <hi>Peace, Peace to him that is far off, and to him that is nigh,</hi> and will heal them. So that ſuch may ſay, <hi>Thanks be to God, they were the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of ſin, but have now from the heart obeyed that form of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine delivered to them,</hi> Rom. 6. 17. Thus he ſuffered <hi>Peter</hi> (when he would not be admoniſhed) to deny him, that he might, ſeeing ſomewhat of the evil fruit of his confidence, be broken off there-from, and have pride hidden from him, and not truſt again in his own ſtrength. See alſo <hi>John</hi> 6. 30-60. and 20. 25-29. and 3. 4-21.</p>
            <p>6. In that our Savior doth not ſimply admoniſh of this evil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the mans as vented forth, but of the root of it, he doth inſtruct us, not onely to cut off the ſuperfluous branches, but even to lay the Axe to the root of the tree, <hi>James</hi> 1. 21. But to this more may be ſaid hereafter.</p>
            <p>In the words themſelves we have,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. An Admonition which our Savior gives; <hi>Take heed, and beware of Covetouſneſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. A Motive, or Argument which he lays down, to ſeal home
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52825:9"/>
the Admonition; <hi>For a mans life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>From the whole Verſe we ſhall note,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That thoſe that hear the Word need to be admoniſhed to take heed, and beware of Covetouſneſs.</item>
               <item>2. That they may take heed, and beware of it in the light and ſtrength of Gods grace.</item>
               <item>3. That the conſideration of this, that a mans life conſiſts not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth, is alſo proper, as viewed in the glorious Goſpel, to move us to take heed, and beware of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. That thoſe that hear the word had need to be admoniſhed to take heed, and beware of Covetouſneſs.</p>
            <p>That this may be of ſome uſefulneſs to us, conſider</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What this Covetouſneſs here admoniſhed of, is.</item>
               <item>2. What contained in the admoniton, <hi>Take heed, and beware of it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. We ſhall demonſtrate it; that they need, and ſhew where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they need to be admoniſhed of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. What this Covetouſneſs here admoniſhed of, is.</p>
            <p>We ſhall firſt ſhew what it is not.</p>
            <p>1. It is not a ſerving God in thoſe works of his providence he gives us to be exerciſed in here under the Sun, and diligence therein; though in ſo doing we may be ſerving our Covetous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination; Yet we are not forbidden to exerciſe our ſelves in any honeſt Trade, Way, or Imployment, though in all our conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations to beware of this iniquity: God appointed to man ſome exerciſe to be exerciſed in while he was in the ſtate of innocency, namely, to dreſs, and to keep the Garden, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 15. And hath ſince given a travel to men to be exerciſed in, <hi>Exod. 20. 9. Eccl.</hi> 3. 10. And warnes of idleneſs, and ſlothfulneſs, and ſhews the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil nature, and fruit of it; Yea and there are commandments given by the Lord Jeſus to the believers, <hi>that if any would not work, neither ſhould they cat,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom. 12. 11. 2 Theſ. 3. 10. Tit.</hi> 3. 14. Yea and the Apoſtles, and their fellow-laborers did worke, and ſo make themſelves an enſample to the beleivers to follow them, 1 <hi>Cor. 4. 11. 12. 2 Theſſ.</hi> 3. 7-9. And not onely is ſuch inſtruction, and example given to the believers in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, but to the Elders of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> how that ſo labouring (as the apoſtle had done) they ought to ſupport the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52825:9"/>
weak, &amp;<hi>c. Acts</hi> 20. 28-25. Yea our bleſſed Savior hath given us an example, who was not onely the reputed Son of a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter, but a Carpenter alſo, <hi>Mark. 6. 3. Luk.</hi> 2. 51.</p>
            <p>2. Nor is it a deſiring of him thoſe things that are needful for our chearful ſeeking after, and glorifying him; in order thereto we may deſire ſuch meat, drink, cloaths, and ſuch a proſpering the work of our hands, as may conduce to our hallowing of his name, and to ſuch an end he hath inſtructed us in that doctrine of right prayer to ſay, <hi>Give us day by day our daily bread,</hi> Phil. 4. 6. Though yet in ſuch deſire alſo Covetouſneſs is to be watcht againſt in the light of the Lord, and we to be ſubmitted to God, and his infinite wiſdome, and faithfulneſs, who knows what is moſt conducible to ſuch an end better than we do; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are we willed by the mercies of God to preſent our bodies to him, to be ordered by him as he ſees good, and taught to pray, <hi>Thy will be done, &amp;c. Give us this day our daily bread, Math. 6. 10, 11. Phil. 4. 5, 6, 7. Pro.</hi> 30. 8, 9.</p>
            <p>3. Nor is it all coveting that we are admoniſhed of, or of all that which is ſo called; we are inſtructed to Covet earneſtly the beſt gifts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 31. and 14. 39. There are alſo the luſts of the ſpirit, effected by ſpirit in the Teſtimony of Jeſus in the ſpirit of the believer, and ſo the ſpirit luſteth againſt the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 17. The new ſpirit and heart of the hearty believer, from the diſcovery; and beholding of the excellency, and comlineſs of Chriſt, his love, and lovelineſs, and having taſted of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs, as a new born babe deſires the ſincere milk of the word; it earneſtly deſires more to know Chriſt, win him, and be found in him, to be conformed to him, and clothed on with the fruit of his righteouſneſs; it pants after, and thirſteth for God, even the living God, and longs, and luſts for him, to ſee further his glory, and power in the Sanctuary (in his Son, and in the aſſemblies of his hidden ones) even as thoſe that cannot be ſatisfied without wiſdom, they (while walking in the ſpirit) ſeek it as men ſeek ſilver; this the one thing they deſire, and for which they have counted, and do count all other things as loſs, and dung, in compariſon thereof; and in perſuing after it, and to the promoting of it, nothing they ſuffer moves them, nor count they their lives dear to themſelves, that they may more know and be made partakers of Chriſt. Oh that we were filled more with theſe luſts of the ſpirit, and were more coveting
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52825:10"/>
thoſe excellent things, that durable riches, and righteouſneſs in Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 4. and 42. 1, 2. and 63. 1-8. <hi>Pro.</hi> 2. 2-6. and 8. 18. <hi>Gal. 5. 16, 17. Phil.</hi> 3. 8-10.</p>
            <p>But the Covetouſneſs here admoniſhed of, is</p>
            <p>An affection, and luſt of the fleſh, in which a man doth love this world, and the things thereof, and (not content with Gods proviſion, allowance, and gift) doth greedily deſire after more of it, that he may be rich in, or toward himſelf.</p>
            <p>1. I ſay, it is an affection, and luſt of the fleſh, as diſtinguiſhed from, and oppoſed to the luſts of the ſpirit (as before) and ſo to ſhew unto us whence it ſprings, namely, from the fleſh, the carnal minde, or wiſdom of the fleſh, which is ſometimes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Covetouſneſs, and ſo oppoſed to Gods teſtimonies, which is the wiſdom from above, to ſhew the nature of it, and that it is the ſource, and fountain of this corrupt affection, and luſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 36. For from this corrupt fountain, this iniquity proceeds, even from that wiſdom which is not from above, it deſcends not, or comes not down from the Father of light, but aſcends out of our hearts, and is earthly (affecting, and luſting after, and leading us to love, minde, and ſavour earthly things) ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual (leading us to judge according to outward appearance, and to look upon, and mind ſeen things which are temporal, and to live by ſight, or ſenſe, as oppoſed to the living by faith) and Deviliſh (as being that which we received from him and are therein like to him, leading us to aſpire after an equality with God, and to have a ſelfe-ſufficiency in our own hands, and to that end to worſhip and ſerve Satan, the god of this world, who beautifies, and commends the things thereof;) <hi>Jam.</hi> 3. 15. Thus our Savior ſaith; From within, out of the heart of men (namely out of that corrupt underſtanding, and judgment that is in him, as of him, received from, and poiſoned by Satan, and ſtrengthened by the principles, and ſpirit of this world) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed evil thoughts (of God, and of our ſelves, and of the things of this world as if bleſſedneſs did conſiſt in them; and in our poſſeſſing abundance of them) and thence proceeds Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Mark.</hi> 7. 21, 22. This carnal mind is enmity againſt God; (he ſaith not, it hath enmity in it, nor onely that it is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to him, for then there might poſſibly be a reconciling of it, that notwithſtanding, but it is enmity it ſelf, made up, and compoſed of nothing elſe, ſo as it can never be reconciled) it is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52825:10"/>
not ſubject to the law of God, nor indeed can be, it may be purged out, and deſtroyed, but can never be reformed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 7. It would perſwade us there is no God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. 1. Or that he is not able, or faithful to give unto us in his way what we ſtand in need of; and that though he hath manifeſted his love to us in Chriſt, and given him for a ſtanding witneſs of it, that we might, when we are in darkneſs, and ſee no light truſt in the name of the Lord, yet this inſinuates to us, that he hath a ſecret will contrary to his revealed, and though he ſpeak us fair, yet there are ſeven abominations in his heart; ſuch blaſphemous thoughts of God iſſue from this fountain of enmity, this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs in the root; and herewith alſo, it ſets a great Iuſtre upon the things here below, as if true bleſſedneſs ſtood herein, and leads to bleſs the Covetous whom the Lord abhors, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. 3. and to judge that if we had an abundance of theſe things we ſhould ſee no ſorrow, yea to look upon it as an undoubted evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God's peculiar love, and favour to us, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11. 5. and from hence ſprings this helliſh luſt, and love to the things in the world, which is like the root of it, and beares it's name; For as the wiſdom of the fleſh is enmity, ſo is the love of the world alſo; and ſo the Apoſtle ſaith; know ye not that the friendſhip (or love) of the world is enmity with God? <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 4. This is like unto, and the ſpawn of the carnal minde, and as the conſequent thereof leads us to labour to be rich; hence that, <hi>Pro.</hi> 23. 4. and 3. 5. It is our wiſdom, and underſtanding that thus perverts us, and leads us to covet greedily, and if rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es be increaſed to truſt in them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28. 4-6.</p>
            <p>2. It is an affection to, and loving the world, and the things thereof; for from our wiſdom's beautifying theſe things the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are placed upon them; the eye of the ſoul fixedly view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe things, affects the heart, and it is ſet upon them, and therefore Covetouſneſs is called the love of money, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 10. And many times lovers of ſilver, is rendred Covetous: ſee <hi>Luk. 16. 14. 1 Tim. 3. 3. 2 Tim.</hi> 3. 2. And this is put in, in this deſcription of Covetouſneſs as a part of it, and immediate cauſe of the eager deſire after more, that by ſhewing more is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in it then a deſire of more, ſome may be undecieved, who are polluted herewith, and yet excuſe themſelves; For ſay ſome (who give too much cauſe to others to ſuſpect their hearts are polluted with this iniquity, by their withholding
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52825:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
more than is meet) we thank God, we are content with what God hath given to us, and gives us in ſerving him in his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and do not deſire anothers, we Covet no mans gold, ſilver, or apparrel, we have enough, and are content with our portion; to ſuch it might be ſaid</p>
            <p>1. Though it were ſuppoſed that what they ſay is true, yet they may be polluted with this evil, for the ſetting the heart on what they have, though honeſtly come by this is Covetouſneſs, <hi>Pſal. 62. 10. Jam.</hi> 4. 4. Our Savior gives the admonition we are ſpeaking to, when the man might be ſeeking onely his own; the Apoſtle inſtructs, and directs that ſuch an one as might be choſen into the office of a Biſhop ſhould not be <hi>not onely greedy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy lucre,</hi> which is the luſt in Covetouſneſs, but alſo <hi>not Covetous,</hi> viz, not <hi>a lover of ſilver, 1 Tim. 3. 3. If any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 15. ſo that did ſuch ſpeak true herein, and were their deſire, or luſt ſo bounded, as that they coveted no more than what is theirs honeſtly, yet if the heart be ſet upon that, and they give their loves thereto, there is in this a treacherous departing from the Lord, the fountain of living waters, and an adulterous going after vain things that cannot profit, and the waters will overflow this lying hiding place; Theſe are dwellers on the earth, here being their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and here their hearts alſo. And yet,</p>
            <p>2. This is ſtill further a lying refuge; For together with, and as the iſſue of this love of money, there is a luſting after more, and though mens hearts perſwade them othewiſe, yet <hi>they are deceitful above all things, and he that truſteth therein is a fool,</hi> Jer. 17. 9. Prov. 28. 26. For when the heart conceives ſuch an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in riches, as the wiſdom of the fleſh perſwades him there is, it then hath an eager deſire after an enlargment of his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and though poſſibly the luſt be not particularly ſet upon this, or that which is our neighbours, yet generally the deſire is wandring after the things of the earth. Hence whereas the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle writing to <hi>Timothy</hi> uſes two expreſſions to ſet forth this iniquity, to wit, <hi>greedineſs of filthy lucre, and Covetouſneſs,</hi> he uſes but the former, writing to <hi>Titus</hi> on a like occaſion, ſee and compare 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 3. with <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 7. to ſignifie that the love of ſilver ends in a greedineſs to more; hence alſo the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> when he admoniſhes, not to love the world, nor the things thereof, he adds, <hi>For whatſoever is in the world, the luſt of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52825:11"/>
fleſh, the luſt of the eye,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is not of the Father;</hi> to ſignifie that the luſt is a concomitant, and conſequent of the love of it, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 15. 16. So the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> when he ſaith, they that will be rich fall into temptation; to demonſtrate it he ſaith, <hi>For the love of money is the root of all evil,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 9, 10. And this leads us to the next branch of the deſcription, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. It is a luſt of the fleſh, in which a man (not content with Gods proviſion, allowance, and gift) doth greedily deſire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter more; &amp; this ſome give as the whole deſcription of it, namely, a deſire of more, and though (as hath been ſeen) more is in it, yet this is alſo a branch of it; From the wiſdom of the fleſh which beautifies the things of this world, and leads us to think there is a real excellency in them, the heart following after it is inclined hereto, and enamour'd hereon, and hence, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether herewith there is an unſatisfied deſire after more, a gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy coveting all the day long; hence Covetouſneſs is called <hi>the luſt of the eyes,</hi> even of the eyes of the ſoul, the mind, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 16. with <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 3. Thus it is ſaid of the king of <hi>Babylon</hi> (whoſe dominion was very large, ſo as he might have been content yet) <hi>He keepeth not at home, but inlargeth his deſire as Hell</hi> (or the grave that ſaith not, <hi>it is enough, Pro.</hi> 30. 16.) and is <hi>as death,</hi> and <hi>cannot be ſatisfied, but gathereth to him all nations, and heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto him all people,</hi> Hab. 2. 5. In which is ſhewed to us the nature of this luſt; And while the heart goes after it, ſuch is it's unſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs that it breaks all bounds; ſuch a man is not content with Gods proviſion, though he hath prepared all things for us in his Son, and made ſuch proviſion in his great, and precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, that in exerciſing our ſelves to godlineſs, he will give us what is needful thereto, the Lord will be our Shepheard there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhall not want; yet here being no ſenſual ſatisfaction, there is a continued craving, as if this were nothing; Yea though he hath given us allowance to ſeek of him day by day our daily bread, who hath alſo power to forgive us our ſins that might cauſe him to withhold it from us, and to ſeek it in ſuch works of his providence as he gives us to be exerciſed in, that we might take our own portion, and give to others, ſo as in all doing it to his glorie; Yea and though he gives to all fleſh their food, and doth men good—filling their hearts with food, and gladneſs; yet as not contented with all this, there is ſtill a cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Give, give, a deſire after the forbidden fruit, as if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52825:12"/>
elſe would make happy, and in the eating of this we ſhould be as Gods, and have a ſelf-ſufficiency in our own hands; hence Covetouſneſs is oppoſed to a being content with ſuch things as we have, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 5. Thus it was with <hi>Ahah;</hi> though he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned the kingdom of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and therefore had large poſſeſſions, yet becauſe <hi>Naboth</hi> would not give the inheritance of his Fathers to him, he was heavy, and diſpleaſed, as if all he had was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. 2-4. Yea thus it was with the firſt man <hi>Adam,</hi> though God had given a world of creatures to him and given al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance to eat of every tree of the garden, the tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and evil onely excepted; yet liſtening to the lye of the tempter, and conceiving, in eating of that tree, he ſhould be ſelf-ſufficient, he conceived a luſt hereto, as if it were beſt, becauſe not allowed; and did eat of the forbidden fruit; and this is ſtill the nature of this iniquity, a man is like the troubled Sea when it cannot reſt; alwayes deſiring, and craving for the poſſeſſing of an abundance, and thinking, Oh could I but at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to ſo much money, or ſo much by the year, then I ſhould be contented, and is even ſick till the deſire be accompliſhed (as <hi>Amnon</hi> was for his ſiſter <hi>Tamar, 2 Sam.</hi> 13. 2-4.) and yet if he attain thereto, that which was at firſt the end of his deſire is now but a means to a further, and he as much unſatisfied as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as was <hi>Amnon</hi> when his former luſt was ſatisfied, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 15. And it cannot be otherwiſe while the heart is inclined to it's covetouſneſs, becauſe there is no reſt to the ſoul in theſe things, all that which is not bread is unſatisfying, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 2. <hi>He that loveth ſilver ſhall not be ſatisfied with ſilver, nor he that loveth abundance with increaſe,</hi> Eccl. 5. 10. Pro. 21. 26. He may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed reſolve with the rich man in the Parable (which our Savior immediately joynes to this admonition, and inſtruction) that he will ſay to his ſoul (when he hath ſo much in his hand as he propoſes to himſelf,) Soul take thy reſt, eat, drink, and be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; but as he never came at it, ſo more generally it is with him that layeth up treaſure for himſelf, and is not rich toward God, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 16-21. He never arrives at that reſt he propoſes to himſelf in theſe things, his Soul ſhall not dwell at eaſe; For theſe things are not of the Father, not the reſt he hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for our weary ſpirits, Chriſt onely is that, and in taking his yoke upon us we ſhall finde it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. 12. and 55. 1, 2. <hi>Math.</hi> 11. 28, 29. Hence our Savior when he is admoniſhing of this ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52825:12"/>
of Covetouſneſs, and ſhewing the unprofitableneſs of it, ſaith, <hi>What ſhall it profit a man if he ſhall gain the whole world, and looſe his own Soul?</hi> Math. 16. 26. He may herein ſecretly intimate, that a man following his own wiſdom hath a will, and luſt for this, even to have all the world in his own poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as it was with that proud King of <hi>Babylon</hi> (as before) yet if he had it, it would not ſo fill his heart, as to ſatiate his deſire, but ſuch is the nature of this diſeaſe of the Soul, that (like the Dropſie, the more they have, the more they crave; and had ſuch a man the whole world (which Satan may promiſe to give him (as he did our Savior) to gain worſhip from him) yet he would ſtill deſire (with him) that there were another world to conquer, and poſſeſs. And as this is the nature of this evil, ſo that he propoſes to himſelf in it, is</p>
            <p>4. That he may be rich in, or toward himſelf, that he may be ſelf-ſufficient, as oppoſed to the being rich towards God; this is the end of his greedy, and Covetous deſire, that he may heap up for himſelf; A man may (as before is ſaid) with Gods allowance deſire of him to give us food convenient, and to bleſs the work of our hands, ſo as herein ſubmitting to God, to this end, that we may be accommodated to ſeek after the Kingdom of God, and the righteouſneſs thereof, that we may more know, and glorifie it, and be rich toward God, in diſpenſing accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our capacities, as he hath given us inſtruction, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, but now the end of this greedy deſire is, that he may lay up for himſelf treaſure on earth, <hi>where moth, and ruſt corrupt, and where thieves break thorow, and ſteal,</hi> of which we are admoniſhed, <hi>Matthew.</hi> 6. 23. We are not forbidden to lay up treaſure for our ſelves, but are allowed, inſtructed, and encouraged to provide our ſelves baggs <hi>which wax not old, a treaſure in the heavens that failes not, to lay up for our ſelves trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in heaven,</hi> and that in giving to them that ſtand in need, as the love of Chriſt conſtraines, <hi>to do good to all, but eſpecially to to the houſhold of faith,</hi> as we have opportunity, with this aſſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, <hi>that our labour of love ſhall not be in vain in the Lord;</hi> And thus doing we ſhall lay up for our ſelves in ſtore a good founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (not for the preſent to build on, or that this ſhould now be the foundation of our faith, and hope, and matter of our feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ground of our rejoycing; no, the bread which he gives, and which believers feed on, is the fleſh of Chriſt which he hath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52825:13"/>
given for the life of the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 51. The ſheep, as thoſe that know not themſelves thereby, nor have this as the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they are built on, they ſhall ſay, <hi>Lord when ſaw we thee an hungred, and fed thee?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Math.</hi> 25. 37-40. Though Chriſt rejoyces in them, as produced by his grace, taking away the mixtures, and they ſhall be rewarded, but) for the time to come, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 19. But this laying up for our ſelves conſiſts notwith this covetouſneſs, it propoſes no ſuch end in it's inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate deſire, it knows not how to be ſubject to the doctrine of God, and it's inſtructions, nor indeed can it be, it is afraid to truſt God, and leads a man to think that what he poſſeſſeth is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and ſecurer, then in the hands of God, and that whatever is thus parted with is loſt for ever; it is indeed a caſting our bread upon the waters, and there may be no recompenſing of it by thoſe to whom it is given, but after many days they ſhall find it, that do it for Chriſt's ſake, even now, as is good, and when evils are upon the earth, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 11. 1, 2. But however in the reſurrection of the juſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. 14. But alas covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had rather have ſome good ſecurity here, than Gods word, it thinkes he is unfaithful, or unable, and hence the end of his deſire whoſe heart goes after it, is to lay up treaſures for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and theirs here, that they may be rich towards them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo as they may not need by a daily exerciſe of faith to go out of themſelves, to ſeek their daily bread of God. Thus the Prophet declares the end of this evil covetouſneſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 9. <hi>We to him that coveteth an evil covetouſneſs, that he may ſet his neſt on high, that he may be delivered from the power of evil;</hi> This is his end, that he may ſet his neſt on high, either that they may be lifted up in ſtation, and condition above the common ſort of men, and have reſpect, and reverence given unto them, that men may bow the knee before them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24. 21. And thus uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally they are lifted up when riches increaſe, even to the diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and deſpiſing thoſe that have not what they have, and hiding themſelves from their own fleſh, (as to doing them good, and as perſons aſhamed to have any familiarity with them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it may tend to the promoting their deſign) and vexed, and diſcontented, if they have not ſuch honour, and reverence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them as they look for, <hi>Eſther</hi> 3. 1-6. and 5. 9. 14.</p>
            <p>2. Or alſo, and rather, by ſetting the neſt on high, may be meant, a being advanced in order to their living, and faring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52825:13"/>
deliciouſly, and injoying ſecurity, and ſo they would ſet their neſt on high, to this further end, that they might be delivered from the power of evil, <hi>Jer.</hi> 22. 23. and 49. 16. <hi>Obad.</hi> 4. That they may be delivered from all evil, and afflictions, that is, that they may be delivered in times of famine: <hi>the rich mans wealth is his ſtrong Tower;</hi> He thinkes he ſhall be provided for, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever wants; He hath goods laid up for many yeares; And ſo when God is ordering ſickneſſes, and diſeaſes, he thinks to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure himſelf, either by removing his habitation, and changing the air, which he may do, that he may eſcape the infection, and diſeaſe; and if it be upon him, yet he hath wherewith he may furniſh himſelf with the beſt, and moſt skilful Phyſicians, and ſo may meet with recovery again. Or if wars ariſe, and God ſend the ſword to the place where he lives; he can remove his dwelling into another place, or country, or if he fall into the danger, his riches will be a ranſom for him, his gift will make room for him: Or if thorow following his covetouſneſs he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch an iniquity of ſhedding of blood, Adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as deſerves to be puniſhed by the Judges, yet his greatneſs is ſuch, that he is above the laſh of the Law, or can eaſily by his bribes pervert judgment, and blind the eyes of the wiſe, that they ſhall not find him guilty; To this end he coveteth greedily, that he may be delivered from the power of evil. Hence the admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, when God's judgments were threatned to be executed upon his people; <hi>let not the rich man truſt in his riches,</hi> Jer. 9. 17-23. <hi>The rich mans wealth is his high Tower, and a ſtrong wall in his own conceit,</hi> Pro. 18. 10, 11. This is covetouſneſs as to it's principle, nature, and end.</p>
            <p>2. What is contained in the admonition, <hi>Take heed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of Covetouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. This is contained, or however ſuppoſed, in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſee, view, and conſider what it is, and the evil, and bitter nature and fruit of it, that ſo we may further beware of it; for how ſhall we beware of that we are ignorant of? that the Soul be without knowledge it is not good, ſafe, or profitable; hence as our Savior when he admoniſheth his diſciples to beware of falſe prophets, in order thereto, he gives them this rule to know them by, <hi>by their fruits ye ſhall know them,</hi> (namely by the fruit of their lips, their doctrines, and by the fruit and effect of thoſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, in which they might perceive they tend to corrupt from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52825:14"/>
the ſimplicity in Chriſt.) <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 15. 16. Implying they could not beware of them unleſs they knew them; ſo may we ſay in this caſe, we ſhall not flee from this dangerous evil, unleſs in ſome meaſure we ſee, and perceive what, and of what nature it is, like that, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. 19. <hi>Know, and ſee that it is an evil, and bitter thing,</hi> &amp;c. And that we may ſee it, ſo as to avoid it, let us not lean to our own underſtanding, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3. 5. Or conſult with the principles, and ſpirit of this world, or the leaven of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees which is hypocriſie, and will more transform us into this iniquity of which they are ſo guilty; But that we may ſee, and take heed of it, <hi>let us take beed according to Gods word, Pſal.</hi> 119. 9. <hi>The commandment is a lamp, and the Law light,</hi> &amp;c. To diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to us, and preſerve us from what is evil, <hi>Pro.</hi> 6. 23. 24. Such is the deceitfulneſs of our wiſdom that it will colour over this ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, as if it were our duty to follow it; perſwading us it is a wiſe, and circumſpect care, and looking after the main, and that we are worſe than inſidels if we lay not up for our ſelves treaſures here on earth. But all things that are reproved are made manifeſt by the light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This gives a faithful, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial diſcovery of it in the croſs of Chriſt, and there ſhews the vileneſs of it, and abominableneſs of inclining the heart there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, after the grace of God hath been bringing ſalvation to us, that we might in his thus rouzing of us, awake, and ſtand up from this dead work; and whoſo looketh into this perfect law of liberty, and continueth, ſhall be preſerved from it, and be bleſſed in his deed; <hi>Oh houſe of Jacob, walk ye in the light of the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 2. 5. Eph. 5. 12-14. Jam. 1. 23-25.</p>
            <p>2. There is further contained in this admonition, an owning, and confeſſing it's vileneſs as diſcovered, and a departing from it, and not coming near to it, a withdrawing from it as from that which is very dangerous, and pernitious; ſo much is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in the admonition. And in that he gives it in two expreſſions he may hereby note the exceeding vileneſs of it, how highly ſoever men eſteem it, to the end we might remove far from it. Indeed (as we have ſeen) 'tis needful hereto in the glaſs of the Goſpel to behold, and view it, but this is not all; For he that is an hearer of the word, and not a doer, hath this great advantage, and price put into his hand, he beholdeth himſelf, luſts, and wayes, and not liking the diſcovery of the word, he goeth his way, hates the light, and cometh not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52825:14"/>
continually to it, and then forgets what manner of man he was; now he may think himſelf to be in a good condition, and free from that which the glaſs diſcover'd him to be guilty of, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 23. 24. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 20. But this is required of us in the light, and ſtrength of his grace, to flee from it, as from the face of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. And indeed this admonition thus doubled, is ſeldom, or never uſed, but here in admoniſhing of this way of iniquity, and elſewhere in admoniſhing of the leaven of the Phariſees, which is hypocriſie, and which prepares men for it; as <hi>Math.</hi> 16. 6. <hi>Mark.</hi> 8 15. Poſſibly to denote this ſin to be more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſinful, and dangerous (as may be after ſhewn) that we may avoid it. And ſo take heed, and beware of it, that is, 1. Of this affection, and luſt of the fleſh, and ſo of the root of it, the wiſdom of the fleſh, and leaven of the phariſees, abſtain from this fleſhly luſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 11. Otherwiſe it will harm us, and break forth into practiſe; For can a man carry fire in his boſom, and not be burnt? Our Savior here doth not ſimply warn of this mans covetous deſire, as vented forth, but of the root of it, to inſtruct us to take heed to our ſelves that our hearts be not defiled and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercharged herewith; obey it not in the luſt, ſee it be ye kept, or preſerved from inclination to it in your hearts; and ſo have no fellowſhip with it, ask not counſel at this ſtock, or the root of it, ceaſe from thine own wiſdom; ſeek not thy direction, and guidance from this in any matter; <hi>Pro.</hi> 23. 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 36. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 3-5. 11. Yea, flee from it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 9-11. Haſten from it with that eagerneſs, and diligence, as the covetous man is purſuing it; haſte, eſcape from it for your life, as thoſe that know the end thereof is everlaſting death. And hate it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18. 21. <hi>Pro.</hi> 28. 16. Abhor it, not as an ordinary enemy, but as an implacable, and irreconciliable one, and therefore ſo deal with it, mortifie it, put it to death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 5, Yea, look upon it as enmity it ſelf againſt God, that can never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled.</p>
            <p>2. And let your converſation in all your actings towards God and men be without it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 5. Take heed, and beware of exerciſing your ſelves in covetous practiſes, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 14. And from theſe we ſhall more eaſily abſtain, and lay apart the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity of naughtineſs, as it flowes forth, and ſhoots out it's ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous branches, if this filthyneſs in the root, affection, and luſt of it be abſtained from, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 21.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:52825:15"/>3. In this admonition as thus doubled, may be ſignified, a readineſs, and inclination, even in thoſe that hear the word, and are diſciples of Chriſt, to have their hearts inclined hereto; hence this with other luſts called their members on the earth, and they ſo oft admoniſhed of it, <hi>Eph. 5. 3-5. Col.</hi> 3. 5. And as this may be intimated to us in the admonition as thus preſt upon them, that even believers have ſin dwelling in them, and the luſt, and affections thereof to be crucified, and abſtained from in the name of the Lord, ſo alſo it may ſhew unto us one reaſon of our need to recieve, and drink down this admonition; for if we had not the root of it in us, or might not be defiled herewith, then there were no need to take heed, and beware of it; But we ſhall add other demonſtrations.</p>
            <p>3. We now come to give ſome demonſtrations, that thoſe that hear the word, and are diſciples of Chriſt need to be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed of this iniquity, and to ſhew wherefore they need it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Demonſtration</hi> 1. Such need to be warned of, and to beware of this iniquity; becauſe when the heart goes after it, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives, and bereaves the ſoul of good, as <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4. 8. And that both of getting good, and doing good.</p>
            <p>1. This covetouſneſs gone after, deprives the foul of getting good, when a price is put into the hand of ſuch an one as is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined thereto, he is ſo prevailed over by this affection, and luſt, that he hath no heart thereto. And that 1. ſometimes it hath ſuch dominion over a man, that it cauſes him to neglect, or not come to, and wait at the poſts of Wiſdoms doors, when he is invited thereto by Wiſdoms ſervants; then (like thoſe in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) they begin to make excuſe; <hi>one hath bought a peice of ground, and he muſt needs go ſee it:</hi> (there was a neceſſity for this, this muſt be done, or otherwiſe he might be blamed of idleneſs, and careleſneſs by others,) <hi>And another had bought five yoke of ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and theſe are to be proved; and a third had married a wife; and therefore he could not come;</hi> (he muſt now take care for the things of the world, and provide for the charge that uſually follows ſuch a condition, that he may have for his wife, and children, and to lay up for them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. 16 20.) See how this luſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued and followed, led the profeſſed Church to reaſon, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 14. 15. They ſaid, <hi>it was vain to ſerve God</hi> (to frequent the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of his people, to ſpeak often one to another of the name of the Lord, or to hear it ſpoken of. Compare it with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52825:15"/>
ver. 16.) and what profit is it that we have kept his obſervations; though great is the gain of godlineſs, yet becauſe it appeared not ſo, but now the times were evil, they might expoſe themſelves to the hatred of men, and come to looſe all (for they that wrought wickedneſs were ſet up) therefore though they had kept his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, yet now becauſe it ſtands not with their outward ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, they are thus reaſoning with unprofitable talk; and ſo how many are there now, that have gladly heard the goſpel of our ſalvation; who becauſe of their love to this preſent world, and leſt they ſhould looſe all, have turned away their eares from the truth, and forſaken the aſſemblies of God's peculiar people, and are turned to fables, and vain things that cannot profit, which is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable to conſider, <hi>Ezek. 19. 12. 14. Math. 19. 21, 22. Heb.</hi> 10. 25. Or</p>
            <p>2. Though this iniquity have not ſuch dominion over them as quite to withdraw them from the aſſemblies of Gods people, but that they whoſe hearts are inclined thereto come, and ſit before him as his people; yet this covetouſneſs withholds<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> good things from them, and bereaves the ſoul of good, and that</p>
            <p>1. Somtimes by minding the things here below, and having been unſober in their exerciſe about them, the outward man is ſo unfitted, and they ſo ſurprized with ſleepineſs, and heavineſs, that they hear little, or nothing that is ſpoken; either their thoughtfulneſs, and carefulneſs, about what they ſhall eat, what they ſhall drink, and wherewith they ſhall be cloathed, or how they ſhall increaſe, and heap up more for themſelves, hinders them, ſo that their heart takes no reſt in the night, as <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2. 23. and 5. 12. Or riſing early, and over-working themſelves, not watching to ſobriety, thereby the body is ſo tired, and unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that either they are aſleep, or though thier eyes are open, yet the heart is aſleep, it ſeizes on them like an armed man. Thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle, when he admoniſheth the believers <hi>not to ſleep as do others,</hi> he adds, <hi>but let us watch, and be ſober,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5. 6. as implying that if we watch not in the light of the Lord againſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and for good, and be not ſober in our uſe of, and exerciſe about things here below, we ſhall be diſpoſed to ſleep as do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and deprive our ſouls of good; For he that ſleepeth in harveſt (when an opportunity is put into his hand for gathering for the winter, for receiving, and laying up knowledge, and hearing for now, and hereafter, ſuch an one) is a ſon that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52825:16"/>
ſhame, <hi>Pro.</hi> 10. 5. Or 2. if it have not ſuch prevalency o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them to the ſo unfitting the outward man, yet while this ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity is retained, and ſerved againſt the light, and inſtructions of the grace of God, it will deprive, and bereave the ſoul of good, and that either</p>
            <p>1. Thorow their delight in, and love to the things of this world, the heart is ſo taken up with this as it's treaſure, that it is far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from him, and from his word, ſo as it becomes unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to them: when any one heareth the word of the kingdom, and underſtands it not (conſiders it not, or ſets not his heart there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to) then cometh the wicked one, and catcheth away that which was ſown in his heart, <hi>Math.</hi> 13. 19. Yea this will ſo ſeize upon one when the heart follows it, that though the outward man be waking enough, yet a man may be ſo unfitted hereby, that he hears nothing, or immediately what is heard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is let ſlip (as I my ſelf have often perceived, and ſpeak as one faulty in this thing) ſo that if he were preſently asked what hath been ſpoken, he could not tell, and ſhould he go about to anſwer, would cauſe ſhame to himſelf, <hi>Mark.</hi> 8. 17. 18. the cares of this world (which are the fruit of covetouſneſs, do ſo overcharge the heart, ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly burden it, that the man is made altogether unmeet for any thing that is good, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 34-36. Or</p>
            <p>2. Though men are diligent in hearing, and attending at the poſts of wiſdoms doors, yet this affection, and luſt followed, leads to pervert what is right, and ſo to turne our table into a ſnare, as it was with them, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. as before is ſaid. It ſo deprives of underſtanding, as to move a man alwayes in hearing to be ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meat for his luſt, and ſo to be wreſting what he heares, as that he may, thorow his own wiſdom, which is enmity againſt God's word, ſeek to ſtrengthen himſelf, and make proviſion for this luſt of the fleſh: Thus it was here in this <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. While our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior was admoniſhing his diſciples in the hearing of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſaving their lives, and ſtrengthening them againſt the fear of parting with them, and ſo conſequently of parting with every thing for his ſake; the man, as overlooking the ſcope, and end of our Saviors words, and onely conceiving that he was a good man, vents forth his covetous deſire to him; there was not the leaſt thing, in the inſtructions, and admonitions given, to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage hereto, yea they were altogether againſt covetouſneſs; and yet ſo bruitiſh will this luſt make a man, as to turn that which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52825:16"/>
might have been for his welfare into a ſnare unto him; Thus we might ſee in many things; when a man hears the Goſpel of Chriſt faithfully, and without hidden things of Diſhoneſty preached; in which is ſhewn to us the greatneſs, and ſtrength of God's love, as manifeſted in Chriſt, and his loathneſs, that men ſhould periſh, and how his grace hath abounded where ſin abounded; this covetouſneſs being inclined to, will now lead a man to ſtrengthen himſelf in his evil way, and ſecretly thus to reaſon; Seeing he is ſo gracious, and ſo cordial a lover of mankind, I ſhall have peace though I walk after the imagination of mine own heart; I may continue in this my ſin, and God will be merciful to me notwithſtanding; Hence the Apoſtle after he had bin ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how God commendeth his love to us in that while we were yet ſinners Chriſt died for us, and the freeneſs, and largneſs of his grace in this gift of grace, that it exceeded the offence of the firſt man, &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. He then, to ſhew how that wiſdom in us, that covetouſneſs in the root, would pervert this, adds; <hi>what ſay we then, ſhall we continue in ſin that grace may abound? God forbid,</hi> Rom. 6. 1-3. ſo when a man with the inſtructions of the grace of God is admoniſhing of ſloathfulneſs in buſineſs; and ſhewing how unſutable it is to the grace of God, and thoſe commandments given us by the Lord Jeſus, and examples ſet before us for our imitation, to be idle, and that, ſuch as will not worke ſhall not eat: now this covetouſneſs, perverting what is right, will both lead a man as with reſpect to himſelf, to be unſober in his exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe about the things here below, and to work, that he may lay up treaſures for himſelf here on earth, and ſuppoſe this to be god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and a vertue, becauſe oppoſite to the former vice, though indeed it is another extream, of which we are warned, <hi>Math. 6. 19. Eph.</hi> 4. 28. Or elſe it will lead him as with reſpect to others to be over quick-ſighted, and ſay others are idle, and will not work, and ſuch ſhould not eat, the Apoſtle hath ſo commanded, and pretend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this to be their duty to withhold from them, when they are ſerving their covetouſneſs; hence the Apoſtle, when he had warned of idleneſs, and commanded with quietneſs to work, and eat their own bread; he adds; <hi>But ye brethren, be not weary of well doing;</hi> as intimating, that the fleſh would be ready to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert this, and lead a man to withhold more than is meet, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 10-13. And ſo when people are low, and in ſtraits, and come to hear the tidings of the freeneſs of God's grace in Chriſt, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52825:17"/>
what this will work in them that receive it with the heart; how this will frame them to be giving all the day long, to give to him that askes, according to our ability, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Oh ſaith this covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, this is a bleſſed doctrine indeed, and theſe are the people we will cleave to, and follow with; while, mean time, their heart goeth after their covetouſneſs, and they profeſſedly follow Chriſt for the loaves ſake, and are ſeeking meat for their luſts, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſider, how this grace comes to ſave them, and in bringing ſalvation, moves, and ſtrengthens, that denying ungodlineſs, and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Or elſe it will cauſe a man to take offence at the light becauſe of it's reproving, and diſcovering quality, and ſecretly to depart from it; ſo as not ſo as not ſo to receive the love of the truth as to be ſaved thereby; it will cauſe a man to hate reproof; ſo that, though ſuch may ſit before God's ſervants, as his people, and hear their words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſhew much love: Yea the Miniſters of Chriſt (in their ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings) may be as a very lovely ſong of one that hath a pleaſant voice, and they hear their words, yet they do them not, becauſe their heart goeth after their covetouſneſs, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 31. 32. This will lead to hate the light, when it diſcovers their deeds to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and to hate thoſe that are faithful reprovers, as thoſe before ſpoken of: <hi>Son of man, ſaith the Lord, the children of they people are talking againſt thee by the walls, and in the doores of the houſes</hi> (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, privately, and ſecretly, ſo as the prophet might not know it, till God revealed it to him,) <hi>and yet they ſay, Come I pray you, and hear what is the word that cometh forth from the Lorde Ezek. 33. 30, 31. Joh.</hi> 3. 19, 20. So the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> alſo ſignifies, and bewailes. <hi>To whom</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall I ſpeak, and give warning, that they may hear; behold their ear is uncircumciſed and they cannot hear</hi> (not hear in hearing, not endure ſound doctrine) <hi>behold the word of the Lord is a reproach to them, they have no delight in it;</hi> Whence was this? <hi>For from the leaſt of them even to the greateſt of them, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one is given to covetouſneſs,</hi> Jer. 6. 10-13. Yea ſo bruitiſh will this make a man, when given to it, as even openly to reject, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, and ſeek to deſtroy the word of the Lord, when it ſtrikes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and ſhews the evil nature, and fruit of it; Or that God will ſo proceed in his judgments, as to ſtrip them of the objects of this luſt: See what <hi>Jehoiakims</hi> wickedneſs was, when he heard the roll read, which <hi>Jeremy</hi> had received from the Lords mouth, and ſaw others cut it, and caſt it into the fire; yet he was not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52825:17"/>
afraid; Yea though ſome made interceſſion that he would not burn it, yet he would not hear; Whence proceeded this open wickedneſs? ſurely from hence; <hi>Thine eyes, and thine heart</hi> (ſaith God to him) <hi>are not but for thy covetouſneſs,</hi> and therefore he could not endure to hear of the King of <hi>Babylons</hi> coming to deſtroy the nation. Compare <hi>Jer.</hi> 36. 23. 29. with Chap. 22. 17. This alſo was the cauſe of their wiſe men's, Prieſts, and Prophets rejecting the word of the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8. 9, 10. Hence they are ſaid <hi>to be ſuch as fear God, who hate covetouſneſs,</hi> Exod. 18. 21. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever certain it is, that though men have received the word of the kingdom in ſome meaſure to purpoſe, yet going out, theſe thornes, the cares of this world, and deceitfulneſs of riches, and luſt of other things entring in, choak the word, and it, and ſo the man, becomes unfruitful, <hi>Math. 13. 22. Mark. 4. 18, 19. Luk.</hi> 8. 14. And this leads to the next.</p>
            <p>2. It bereaves, and hinders the ſoul of good, namely of doing good, and ſo conſequently of being further made partakers of it, and injoying it; For if we be wiſe, we ſhall be wiſe for our ſelves, and ſo 1. it hinders from doing good, with this worlds good, which he is putting into our hands, that according to what we have, we might do good to all men, and eſpecially to the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith, and in doing which, as moved, and inſtructed by the grace of God, we might in ſome meaſure adorn the doctrine of God our Savior; and ſo either 1. it will ſhut up the bowels of our compaſſion when opened, that we ſhall not be faithful, as is required of ſtewards: God's end in giving to us the things of this world is, that we ſhould according to our ability do good therewith in our life time, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3. 12. And hence I conceive they are called another mans, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 13. Not onely becauſe they paſs from one to another, and no man can be ſure of them, but as they received them from others (for they brought nothing into the world with them) ſo it is certain, they ſhall carry nothing out with them: But alſo becauſe he is intruſting men with the things of this life as ſtewards, who muſt give an account hereof to him; he is putting them into their hands, that according as he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing, and moving them they ſhould diſpenſe to others, and thoſe that are rich might be rich in good workes, ready to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to the needs of others; even as it is with ſtewards, that which is committed to them is not that they ſhould lay it up for themſelves onely, but that according to the inſtruction of their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52825:18"/>
Lords, they might take their own portions, and diſpenſe thereof to others of their fellow-ſervants in the family; ſo he is giving theſe things into our hands, that we might herewith make to our ſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs, with this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain riches: But now this Covetouſneſs retained and ſerved, ſhuts up the bowels of our compaſſions, when God is opening them on ſight of our brothers need. Thus it was with the rich man, he had an opportunity to have made <hi>Lazarus</hi> his friend, with this Mammon of unrighteouſneſs, but neglected it; and this our Savior adds, after he had been inſtructing to faithfulneſs in diſpoſing what is committed to us, and admoniſhing of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, as intimating, this was the root of it, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 9-25- This alſo was the cauſe of the great evil of the fool mention'd in the parable, in this, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. when his ground brought forth plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, he thus reaſons with himſelf; what ſhall I do becauſe I have no room where to beſtow my fruits? (had he obſerved the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of the grace of God, he ſhould not have been at a loſs for this, for the poor are always with us, that we might do good to them, and refreſh their bowels, in relieving their neceſſities, this he never thought of, but) he ſaid, <hi>This will I do, I will pull down my barn, and build greater, and there will I beſtow all my fruits, and my goods,</hi> &amp;c. This man God calls <hi>fool,</hi> becauſe he thought not of laying up his treaſure better, or in a better place, even in heaven, and this was the iſſue of his covetouſneſs; and hence it is immediatly joyned to the admonition we are ſpeaking to, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 15-20. And ſuch a fool is every one that layeth up treaſures for himſelf, and is not rich toward God, ver. 21. 2. Or if it have not ſuch dominion over us as quite to ſhut up the bowels of our compaſſion, but we are diſpenſing to others; yet ſtill this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs conſulted with, and yeilded to, will hinder, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of good, and that either</p>
            <p>1. By cauſing us to do what we do niggardly, and ſparingly, and ſo not as a matter of bounty, but of covetouſneſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 5, 6. And to do what we do grudgingly, as that which is a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous thing, and makes us ſad, and ſorrowful to part with any thing; or at beſt to do it of neceſſity, becauſe we muſt do it, it is our duty to do it, and ſo do it according to the oldneſs of the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and not with a chearful, willing, and prepared minde, and then it is not accepted, but a dead work, and for which there is no reward. Compare 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 7. and 8. 12. with 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 16, 17.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52825:18"/>
Indeed the doing what we do out of neceſſity, and becauſe it is our duty ſimply, this is of high account with ſome men, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be teachers of the law, and know not what they ſay, nor whereof they affirme; and therefore the great motive they uſe to preſs others forward to any good work is, Becauſe it is mens du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do it; and ſo theſe leaders of the people (who as they are too like the Phariſees in being oppoſers of the grace of God to ſinners, ſo in this that they are covetous) teach men to erre in every work of their hand; but ſuch a doing onely, is unacceptable with God, for he loves a chearful giver; And to this, I ſay, this evil root leads men, to do things of neceſſity, and therewith alſo ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to withhold in their givings more than is meet (as <hi>Pro.</hi> 11. 24.) and keeps them from abounding in the work of the Lord; hence the Apoſtle when he gives us commandments by the Lord Jeſus to thoſe things in which liberality, and chearfulneſs is to exerciſed, he warnes of this iniquity, <hi>Heb. 13. 1-7. Let</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>brotherly love continue</hi> (even that peculiar manner of love with which they are to be loved, and which leads us to do good to them, <hi>eſpecially who are of the houſhold of faith, otherwiſe we ſhall love in word, and in tongue, not in deed, and in truth,</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 17, 18. Jam. 2. 14-17.) <hi>Be not forgetful to entertain ſtrangers,</hi> &amp;c. (to take them in, <hi>Math.</hi> 25. 35. Lodg them, and uſe hoſpitality to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 10. <hi>Job.</hi> 31, 32.) Remember them that are in bonds (eſpecially for the Goſpel, and ſo remember them as that brotherly love may continue in the exerciſe of it toward them, in coming unto them, and viſiting them, giving meat to them that are hungry, <hi>&amp;c. Math.</hi> 25. 35, 36.) Remember them who have the rule over you, (not onely in reaping their ſpiritual things, but in diſpenſing to them of our carnal things, <hi>&amp;c. 1 Cor. 9. 11. Gal.</hi> 6. 6-10.) Now that we may thus love in truth, and walk in the exerciſe of love, he doth between theſe inſtructions, inſert this admonition; <hi>let your converſation be without covetouſneſs,</hi> as ſinifying that otherwiſe we ſhall not do, or do negligently, and grudgingly what his grace requires of us:</p>
            <p>2. Or elſe, in ſhewing love, this luſt followed will lead us to ſeek after filthy lucre, &amp; ſo to the inriching our ſelves; to love them that love us, to do good, and lend, hoping for ſomewhat again, and then what thanks ſhall we have, or good ſhall we do; <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. 32-35. Hence the Apoſtle when he inſtructs to walk in love, adds; <hi>But covetouſneſs let it not be once named amongſt you,</hi> Eph 5. 1-3.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52825:19"/>
implying, that if this be not watcht againſt in the light of the Lord, it will lead us in walking in love to be aiming at our own advantage, or providing for the preſent time, or time to come, when we may poſſibly fall into want alſo; or elſe to do it out of a deſire of vain-glory, that we may have praiſe of men, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 2-4.</p>
            <p>2. It hinders and deprives the ſoul of good, with reference to, and in their ſpeakings to others, in which they ſhould ſpeak as the oracles of God (both as to the matter, in ſpeaking as they ſpeak to every thing, and as to the manner, in ſo ſpeaking as they inſtruct, and move us, namely that abſtaining from fleſhly luſt, they have their converſation honeſt, chaſt to the deſign of Chriſt) that God in all things may be glorified by Jeſus Chriſt; and ſo 1. it ſometimes keeps thoſe that believe on Chriſt from confeſſing him, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9. 59, 60. and eſpecially in times of tribulation, and perſecution for Chriſt's ſake; Oh how will this covetouſneſs inclined to perſwade men to favour themſelves, and to keep their mouths as with a bridle when there is danger, for fear of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their liberties, and goods, and bringing upon themſelves ſhame, reproach, and poverty; inſinuating this to be the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt folly that can be; this will thruſt ſore at men, that they may conceal the words of the Holy One; and therefore alſo our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior here may give this admonition ſo generally as to include his diſciples, <hi>that they ſhould take heed, and beware of covetouſneſs,</hi> when he had been inſtructing them to hold forth the word of life; and therein to partake of the afflictions of the Goſpel; leſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they ſhould be aſhamed of the Teſtimony of Chriſt. This may be included in the cauſe of the Rulers not confeſſing him, who believed on him; leſt they ſhould be put out of the ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, and the reby be deprived of the advantage, and honor that hitherto they had received, <hi>Job.</hi> 12. 42. This made <hi>Demas</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Apoſtle, becauſe he loved this preſent world, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 10. And ſo the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>while ſome have coveted after mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, they have erred from the faith,</hi> (both from their holding faſt the profeſſion of it, and ſo perſiſting from the faith it ſelfe, or from the believing of it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 10. Or elſe 2. if ſuch ſeem to hold on their former way, and pretend to ſeek the good of men in their confeſſion of Chriſt, yet retaining a ſecretinclination to this hurtful root, it will pervert them in their way, and render them unfruitful, and unſucceſsful; hence the Apoſtle, in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing <hi>Timothy,</hi> and directing him in his choice of thoſe that are
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52825:19"/>
meet to go before others in the word of the Lord, tells him, <hi>that ſuch an one muſt not be greedy of filthy lucre, not covetous,</hi> 1 Tim. 3. 3. Tit. 1. 7. So he ſaith of Deacons alſo, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3 8. ſignifying that ſuch an one as is given to this evil is unmeet for this ſervice; For either it will lead men to ſpeak ſuch things as are not meet, and ſo to corrupt the word of God, as to ſuit mens humors, and teach things they ought not, for this filthy lucres ſake, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 11. when there is hope of profit, to hate their brethren in their heart, and not to rebuke them, but ſuffer ſin upon them, leſt by dealing plainly and faithfully, they fail of their expectation, which was too uſual with Prieſts and Prophets formerly; <hi>For</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>every one from the leaſt to the greateſt is given to covetouſneſs,</hi> &amp; (from hence) <hi>from the Prophet even<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the Prieſt, every one dealeth falſly; for they have healed the hurt of the daughter of my people ſlightly, ſaying, peace, peace, when there is no peace,</hi> Jer. 6. 13, 14. and 8. 10, 11. In which (I conceive) the Prophet declares the iniquity both of prieſts and people; the people they were given to it, and could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſound doctrine; and the heart of Prieſts and Prophets was given generally to it, and therefore that they might bear rule and the people might put into their mouths, they ſuited their humors and ſowed pillos under their elbows, and ſo daubed them up with untemper'd mortar, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 3. And oh that none of the ſpiritual Prieſthood were thus polluted with this iniquity, that they were not too much overlooking the evils of ſuch as from whom they hope to receive gain, ſo as not to deal faithfully with them, in warning of them; the Apoſtle when he ſaith, <hi>I ceaſed not to warn every one, &amp;c.</hi> adds <hi>I have coveted no man's gold,</hi> &amp;c. Implying, that if he had, this might have kept him from dealing faithfully, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 31-33. Or toward ſuch as are poor, it will lead them to deal with ſuch in proud wrath, to be too quick-ſight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in beholding their moats, and to be too ſharply reproving them, or unſeemlily backbiting them as guilty of many evils, when as were they in them that might anſwer their covetous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, they would ſcarcely be taken notice of; too much like thoſe, <hi>Mica.</hi> 3. 5. He that puts not into their mouths, they even pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare war againſt him, and however this iniquity being yielded to, and ſuffered to bring forth fruit, will render a man unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in their ſervice, for it will provoke God to withdraw, and withhold the preſence of his ſpirit from them, ſo as that though they be in pain, and labor to bring forth, they ſhall work no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52825:20"/>
For though the covetous bleſſeth himſelf, yet the Lord abhors him, <hi>Pſal. 10. 3. Iſa.</hi> 57. 15. He will not have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with them, ſuch ſhall not ſtand in his ſight as owned, and approved by him; and therefore what fitneſs ſoever otherwiſe they might have, and how meet ſoever they may think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be for inſtructing others; Yet they will not proſper, while they hold faſt this deceit, and come not to the fountain to be waſhed from it; yea while they in preaching the word go about to reprove others for being polluted with this iniquity, and they themſelves are not waſhed from it, men will ſecretly loath what ever they ſay, and are even ſtrengthued in their evil ways, and take occaſion to ſpeak evil many times of the way of truth, while they ſay to others, they ſhall not covet, or ſteal, and yet they themſelves take liberty to do it themſelves, by occaſion hereof, the name of God is blaſphemed among the Gentiles, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 19-24. Hence the Apoſtle renders this as a reaſon of their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfulneſs, and that their entrance was not in vain, <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we uſed not at any time a cloak of covetouſneſs, God is witneſs,</hi> 1 Theſ. 2. 1-5. Therefore this iniquity is to be fled from, and hated, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it deprives and bereaves the ſoul of good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Demon. 2. This covetouſneſs, the love of money, is the root of all evil,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 10. Therefore to be abſtain'd from, and mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; all evil ſprings from it, as from it's root; though there may be other roots alſo, yet this is expreſly ſaid ſo to be; and ſo it is the root of ungodlineſs, and unrighteonſneſs, or worldly luſts.</p>
            <p>1. It is the root of ungodlineſs. The firſt commandment is, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart,</hi> &amp;c. Math. 22. 37. But this ſerved leads us to hate him; <hi>For no man can ſerve two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, he will love the one and hate the other,</hi> &amp;c. Luk. 16. 13, 14. Now covetouſneſs being a love of this world, it neceſſarily ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, and leads to an hatred of God, while it is ſerved; hence the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>If any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 15. that is, God's love towards us in Chriſt dwells not richly in ſuch an one; and alſo the love of the Father, namely, love to, and of him with all the heart, is not in ſuch an one, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 3. and ſo</p>
            <p>1. It leads us to ſet up ſome other object, and thing before us as God, yea covetouſneſs is ſaid to be idolatry, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 5. And the covetous man an idolater, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 5. The heart of ſuch an one ſecretly depart from the Lord, and gives that honour to money,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52825:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that is onely due to Jeſus Chriſt, and God in him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 5. It leads to bowing down to it, and to be truſting in it, as that which will protect from the power of evil; hence that inſtruction; <hi>Charge them that are rich, that they truſt not in uncertain riches;</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 17. And ſo to expect help from this in the time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>Pſal. 49. 6. Hab.</hi> 2. 9. And as thoſe that remember the name of the Lord make their boaſt of him, ſo theſe in their riches, (or if they have them not, yet conceive ſuch an exellency in them, that they would boaſt in them if they had them) and even bleſs themſelves; <hi>the covetous bleſſeth himſelf, and abhorreth God,</hi> Pſal. 10. 3. Zech. 11. 5. yea their hearts may be ſo lifted up when rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es are increaſed, that they may ſay they are God, <hi>Ezek<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 28. 2-9. And ſo ſet their mouthes againſt the heavens, <hi>&amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 73. 3-9.</p>
            <p>2. It leads men to worſhip God by ſome other <hi>medium</hi> than Jeſus Chriſt, as declared in the Teſtimony, who is the onely way of approach to God, and either voluntarily to ſerve other things, or God by other things, that they may injoy plenty of all things, and it may go well with them, as it was with them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 44. 15-19. Or which is of the ſame nature, to worſhip God by mens precepts, and be the ſervants of men in their ſpirits, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and by obſerving theſe to think God will accept them; yea and to come by their riches as the way to God, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11. 5. Or elſe unwillingly they will conform to men, and worſhip, and have their fear taught by their traditions rather than to be expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the danger of looſing the object of their hearts delight, and deſire, and ſo will many times comply with men in their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions, worſhippings of images, &amp;c. even to the wounding of their conſciences, that they may ſecure their ſubſtance to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and ſo it is true, whether willingly, or unwillingly, <hi>all the world wonders after the beaſt, and all the inhabiters of the earth have been made drunk with the wine of the fornication of the whore;</hi> ſuch one way or other ſhall be defiled with women (the whore, or her daughters) ſo as to partake of their pollutions, either ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a conſederacy, or fearing their fear, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 3, 4. and 14. 4. and 17. 2. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 9, 10.</p>
            <p>3. It leads to take God's name in vain, and that by ſwering curſing, and ſo proſaining his name, <hi>Judg.</hi> 17. 2. Yea and by forſwearing, breaking vows, and promiſes made to him, and of which he is witneſs, when ſuch an one hath been ſwearing to his own hurt, or vowing and promiſing ſuch things as ſtand, or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52825:21"/>
prove in concluſion, croſs to their greedy deſign. Thus <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and the people polluted God's name, in that, when they had made a vow; and covenant to give libety to the ſervants, they broke it, and it may ſeem this was the cauſe of it; becauſe the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it conſiſted not with their profit, <hi>Jer.</hi> 34. 8-16. <hi>Far from the leaſt to the greateſt every one was given to covetouſneſs;</hi> and indeed often times this leads to breach of covenant, and promiſe, even when the promiſe made hath tended to their more free, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſeeking the kingdom of God, yet now they cannot keep it, they pretend, becauſe it will be of great hurt, and prejudice to them; they have bought a peice of ground, or have a farm in their hands, and they muſt needs go (they have a neceſſity, or a neceſſity lies upon them ſo to do) and ſee it, look after, and improve it, and therefore they deſire, and hope they ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. 18. But ſhall he proſper that doth ſuch things? Yea more generally this leads to take his name in vain, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieve his grace in vain, while, though men call themſelves of the holy city, and cry <hi>the temple of the Lord are we,</hi> yea and ſome of them may have been brought nigh to him by the blood of Jeſus, and ſerved him in his temple, yet they run with others to the ſame exceſs of riot, in ſurfetting, and drunkeneſs, or in cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, and wantonneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and have fellowſhip with men in their unfruitful workes of darkneſs; Oh how do ſuch cauſe the name of God, and his doctrine to be blaſphemed! <hi>Pro.</hi> 30. 9. How doth it open the mouths of men (not againſt this covetouſneſs the root hereof, but) againſt the glorious Goſpel, as if it were a miniſtry of ungodlineſs? how are the profane ones gladded, to ſee that thoſe who formerly had eſcaped the pollutions of the world thorow the knowledge of the Lord and Savior, and were ſeperate from them; that now they are turned with the dog to his vomit, and that ſuch can keep company with them, and ſwear, and drink; yea and ſomtimes be drunk alſo? this is a ſport to them, and they are ſtrengthned in their wickedneſs, and ready to ſay, it is in vain to ſerve God; and yet to this, in times of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation eſpecially, will covetouſneſs lead one, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 16-18. <hi>They that will be rich</hi> (that have a deſign, and reſolution ſo to be) <hi>fall into temptation, and a ſnare,</hi> (into the fear of man, in which they are intangled, and fetter'd that they dare do nothing that may offend them, <hi>Pro.</hi> 29. 25.) <hi>and</hi> (thence) <hi>into many fooliſh, and hurtful luſts, which drown men in deſtruction, and perdition,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:52825:21"/>
1 Tim 6. 9. This will lead men into fooliſh luſts, even into ſuch as ſeem not to ſtand with their deſign, ſuch as drunkenneſs, in which they ſpend that they love ſo dearly; yet their having fellowſhip with men herein, tending to their getting, or keeping what they have, by gaining, and ſecuring the favour of the world to them; hence it ultimatly tends to their deſign.</p>
            <p>4. It leads to profane God's reſt, to count Jeſus Chriſt, who is the reſt (in whom God hath taken up his reſt, and well-pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and the reſt he hath prepared for our weary ſpirits, and the refreſhing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 3, 4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28. 12.) a common, and profane thing, and inſufficient, to ſatiate our ſouls, and therefore leads to take up reſt, and ſeek ſatisfaction in that which is not bread, and therefore will not ſatisfie; thus the fool in the parable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves; <hi>I will ſay to my ſoul, take thy reſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 19. though he never came at it, nor will this ſatisfie, and therefore it is a vain converſation here to be ſeeking it. Yea and it leads to profane his holy-day (that time he hath ſet apart for a ſolemn waiting upon him, and thereto ceaſing from our own works, to ſignifie to us, that it is he that doth ſanctifie us, and that, in ceaſing from our own works, and by faith entring into his reſt, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. 13. 17.) I ſay it leads to profane it, not onely by ſaying, <hi>when will the ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath be gone, that we may ſet forth wheat?</hi> as counting that a weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome time as it was with them, <hi>Amos.</hi> 8. 5. but more groſly; either by over-working themſelves, and their ſervants in the ſix days, that they are meet for no hallowing his day; or imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in doing their ordinary ſervile work, to the depriving them of waiting upon him, and provoking Gods wrath, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13. 15-22. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 21-27. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. 3. 7. 13.</p>
            <p>2. And ſo alſo, this is the root of unrighteouſneſs, or worldly luſts, and contrary to our loving our neighbour as our ſelves, as the grace of God doth inſtruct, yea and as he is thereby working it in us; <hi>and the righteouſneſs of the law ſhall be fulfilled in them who are in Chriſt Jeſus, who walk not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit,</hi> even the righteous affections, and ſervices thereof, not by our own wiſdom, and ſtrength in obſerving the law as a law of works, and ſo looking on it as our duty, but in ceaſing from our own works, and entring into God's reſt, and thorow the ſpirit <hi>waiting for the hope of righteouſneſs by faith,</hi> Rom. 8 4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5, 6. 16. 21, 22. To this love of our neighbour, covetouſneſs is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 9. And ſo it leads</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:52825:22"/>1. To diſhonor Parents, whether natural, or civil, or thoſe that by God's providence are ſet over us in that ſtead; and not to give them that honor, reverence, or obedience which is due to them, and to be given them in the Lord, even in the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, and fear of him, and for the Lords ſake, in reverence to his wiſdom, and faithfulneſs, who hath ſet them in ſuch a ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of command, and authority, and us in the place of ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. This will lead us to withhold from natural parents that honor due to them, in which is included a requiting them, in providing for them, and maintaining them when in ſtraits, and brought to poverty: Thus the Phariſees who were covetous, they honor'd not their parents, yea and taught others to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs the command of God, and pretended godlineſs in thus tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing. <hi>God commanded</hi> (ſaith our Savior) <hi>ſaying, honor thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Mother,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But ye ſay, whoſoever ſhall ſay to his Father, or Mother it is a gift, by whatſoever thou maieſt be profited,</hi> (or it is Corban) a thing devoted and ſet apart for religious, and pious uſes (poſſibly for the maintenance of ſuch teachers, or ſuch Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaical Miniſters) he ſhall be free from the obligation of Gods law; or is obliged to keep his former vow, and ſo cannot honor his Father, <hi>&amp;c. Math.</hi> 15. 3-6. <hi>Mark.</hi> 7. 9-12. And this leads to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel againſt authorities, and rulers ſet over us, and ſo to reſiſt the ordinance of God, that men may ſet their neſt on high, while yet they may pretend Godlineſs for ſo doing, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 2. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 11-17. And it leads others who would be accounted the moſt free from rebellion, to diſhonor, or not to honor principalities, and powers, when their profit lies at ſtake. The grace of God inſtructs to render to all their due, <hi>tribute to whom tribute, cuſtom to whom cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom,</hi> &amp;c. Now how many are there, yea and of thoſe alſo who repute themſelves, and would be reputed the beſt ſubjects, and moſt loyal to the higher powers, who yet would withhold from them what by Law or Cuſtom is due to them, and defraud them thereof; yea many times ſteal their Cuſtoms; and if they are in ſuch places as they can eaſe themſelves of that which of right they ought to pay, they will rather lay it upon others ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and however it is not of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſcience, but for wrath they do what they do, and the root thereof is the love of money, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1-7. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 1-3. It's a rare thing to be found, that a man will out of conſcience toward God give to the authorities what appertains to them, when they can by any means avoid it, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52825:22"/>
cleverly come off, nor will this be done, unleſs covetouſneſs be abſtained from; ſo far will covetous perſons be from imitating our Savior, who would pay what he was not obliged to, leſt he ſhould offend; that on the other hand, they will ſeek to keep, and hold what they are ingaged to pay from thoſe in power.</p>
            <p>2. So alſo it leads to murther, or kill another, and to thoſe things which are included in, and lead to the murthering our neighbor, ſuch as anger, wrath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when it is without cauſe, or exceeds the due bounds, as to the meaſure, or continuance thereof, as our Savior ſignifies, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 21-23. How will this iniquity followed lead men to have an evil eye at, and envy the good, and proſperity of another, <hi>Pro.</hi> 28. 22. And to be angry with, and hate thoſe that are faithful reprovers, <hi>Amos.</hi> 5. 10-12. Or ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to wiſh, and deſire the death, and removal of ſuch, by whom they may be inriched; yea and actually to ſeek their deſtruction by whom they may increaſe to themſelves, and ſatisfie their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous deſire; This led <hi>Judas</hi> to betray his Maſter; <hi>Jezabel,</hi> and <hi>Ahab</hi> to conſpire, and compaſs the death of <hi>Naboth;</hi> Yea and it leads thoſe in power to murther the innocent, and thoſe that are quiet in the land; hence the Lord ſaith to <hi>Jehoiakim; thine eyes, and thine heart are not but for thy covetouſneſs, and</hi> (as the fruit here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) <hi>to ſhed innocent blood,</hi> Jer. 22. 17. Ezek. 22. 13-17. Yea how doth this lead them that have the faith of our Lord Jeſus, to have it with reſpect of perſons; and ſo to deſpiſe, ſlight, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue the poor, and in their aſſemblies to bid them to ſet at their foot-ſtool (while they ſhew great reſpect to ſuch as have gay apparel, eſpecially if they have but any hope of advantage from them) and herein they are guilty of murder, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 1-11. And to hate ſuch as rebuke them faithfully, eſpecially if they are poor in this world; <hi>and he that hates his brother is a murderer,</hi> 1 Joh. 3 15. Yea whence come wars, and fightings amongſt us, ſtrifes, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, confuſions, &amp; every evil work, come they not from this love to, and friendſhip of the world? See <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 1-4. and ſo from that wiſdom from beneath, which is covetouſneſs in the root, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3. 14-16. Theſe all are joyned with this iniquity, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 29, 30.</p>
            <p>3. So it leads unto, and is the root of Adultery, Fornication, and ſuch filthyneſs of the fleſh as ſhould not once be named a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſaints. Indeed as covetouſneſs is more largly taken, ſo this filthyneſs is included in it, it being ſuch an iniquity as in which men, or women not content with God's allowance, and gift,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52825:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
covet after ſome ſuch perſon as is forbidden him of God, and that which leads to this iniquity is called, coveting our neighbors wife, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He hath allowed every man, according to his inſtructions, to have his own wife, and every woman her own husband, but this luſt inſinuates to us that ſtollen waters are ſweet, and that that onely will give ſatisfaction which is the forbidden fruit, and ſo perſwades that evil is good, and good evil; it is perſwading that the unlawful injoyment of ſuch, or ſuch a perſon will give reſt to us, not becauſe it will do ſo in concluſion, for when their luſts are ſatisfied, they are as far from having what they propoſed to themſelves as before; and whereas they conceited the having fellowſhip with ſuch an one as is forbidden of God would tend much to their contentment, and therefore they covet greedily, and are even ſick of this carnal love, yet it proves contrary to their expectation, and they are as far from reſt as ever: Yea the object of their love, and luſt, many times comes to be ſubject of their hatred: As in the caſe of <hi>Amnon.</hi> He loved his fair ſiſter <hi>Tamar,</hi> and he was ſo vexed that he fell ſick for her, as thinking it hard for him to do any thing to her; but when through the ſubtlety of his friend he had accompliſht his deſire, he hated her exceedingly (though ſhe was fair, and a kings daughter, and he had ſo paſſionatly luſted after her before) <hi>ſo that the hatred where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hated her, was greater than the love wherewith he had loved her, 2 Sam.</hi> 13. 1-4. 15. And as covetouſneſs is more ſtrictly taken for a love of, and deſire after riches, ſo it is that which leads perſons that are capable, to the committing of this ſin of uncleanneſs; hence the admonition of having our converſation without covetouſneſs, is immediately ſubjoyned, after the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>Wheremongers and adulterers God will judge,</hi> Heb. 13. 4, 5. As if he would ſignifie, that the having our converſation with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs will apt, and lead to that uncleanneſs: ſo they that are freinds, or lovers of the world are called <hi>Adulterers,</hi> and <hi>Adultereſſes,</hi> Jam. 4. 4. Poſſibly, not onely becauſe hereby their hearts are departing from the Lord, and ſo they commit ſpiritual adultery, but alſo to ſignifie that the love of the world leads to outward and bodily adultery. Now this love of money is the root of this evil either indirectly, or more directly.</p>
            <p>1. Indirectly, as when it leads into ſuch paths as occaſion mens committing ſuch iniquity, as when perſons in marrying marry not according to the inſtructions of the grace of God, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52825:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
are unequally yoked, and joyn themſelves with ſuch as they cannot love, as is meet in that relation; hence having no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in their own yoke-fellows, they even expoſe themſelves, and their yoke-fellows to any temptation, and are many times taken in this ſnare of the Devil; how many are there that pretended love to, and are marryed with ſuch as they ſecretly loath, or however have no delight in, becauſe their heart is inclined to it's covetouſneſs, and they thus fit themſelves for this filthineſs of the fleſh. Hence the Apoſtle when he aſſerts the honorableneſs of marryage, and condemns whoredom, he adds, <hi>let your converſation be without covetouſneſs,</hi> Heb. 13. 4, 5. Or when men, or women, live not with each other according to knowledg, but abſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves one from another, and defraud one another too long for filthy lucres ſake, they lay open themſelves, and their relation many times to the luſts of others, and which ever perſon offends, not onely is that party guilty of the ſin which commits it actually, but the other who thus occaſioned it, he, or ſhe, cauſeth the other to commit adultery; like that, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 32. Or when more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, perſons aim at advantage, that they may have better trading, and ingage others to them, or have the favor of the world, and be continued in the camp, and lookt upon as ſuch as are of the world's confederacy, and no diſſenters from them, oh how powerful will this be to betray them to this luſt, eſpecially when the days are evil, and men generally make a mock of this ſin, and practiſe it, or when the times are like ſpoken of, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7. 3 4 7.</p>
            <p>2. Directly, many times this is the root of Adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in men and women: though moſt frequently in the latter: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times men, when poor, and in ſtraits, not exerciſing themſelves to the Law of the Lord, nor obſerving its inſtructions, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit lewdneſs with women that may maintain them, that they may ſee no want, and ſo, though not very ordinarily, whores give gifts to their lovers (as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 33, 34. Where, though ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual fornication be directly ſpoken of, yet there is reſpect had to this bodily, and we may be inſtructed what the adultreſſes exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe is at ſome times.) But moſt frequently women expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the luſts of men for filthy lucre ſake; hence ſo often there is mention made of the hire of an harlot, <hi>Gen. 38. 16. 17. Pro.</hi> 6. 26. and 29. 3. <hi>Hoſ. 9. 1. Mica.</hi> 1. 7. Yea this covetouſneſs ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times prevails over women to the committing this iniquity, when their luſt to this uncleanneſs is not otherwiſe ſo great, or they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52825:24"/>
are not inordinately inclined to it; and eſpecially when they have not in ſome meaſure learnt to be content with the condition they are in, but are perſons of appetite; that love the beſt meat, and drink, and to pamper themſelves therewith, ſuch are in very great danger, when God brings them into poverty, to be led captive by the luſts of ſuch men as can anſwer their covetous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, and to bow down themſelves unto them, that they may be accommodated according to their deſire; and this branch of covetouſneſs, this deſire to fare deliciouſly, and to pleaſe our appetites, as it leads to whoredom, and adultery, that they may have money to ſpend upon this luſt; ſo alſo the more they pleaſe their appetite in the beſt meat, and drink, the more hereby they inrage the luſt of uncleanneſs; hence they are joyn'd together, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 3. and <hi>chambering, and wantonneſs</hi> ſet as the conſequent of <hi>ſurfetting</hi> and <hi>drunkenneſs, Rom.</hi> 13. 13. and they ſaid to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file the fleſh, who feed themſelves without fear,</hi> Jude 8. 11. good therefore it is to receive that admonition, <hi>Pro.</hi> 23. 1-3. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, though there be not a ſtrong inclination to faring delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, yet ſtill the love of money will prevail, if ſerved, to lead to ſatisfie the baſe luſts of men, if perſons have any inclination thereto, and are poor, when ſtrongly importuned, with aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or hope of ſome conſiderable advantage, and when they have opportunity, and God permits them for their former hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their hearts againſt the reproofes of his inſtruction.</p>
            <p>4. So it leads to ſteal from, and wrong another: and by ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and robbing is not meant onely thoſe groſs acts which the law lays hold on, and which is ſo ſhameful amongſt men; but any ſuch like thing in which another is injured of what appertains to him, as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 10. If he beget a ſon that is a robber, a ſhedder of blood, and that doth the like to any of theſe things: hence even Law-makers (who did not break ſecretly into other houſes, and ſo ſteal as the law might take hold of them, yea they had a law for what they did, yet) are ſaid, <hi>to take away the right from the poor, that widdows might be their prey, and that they may rob the fatherleſs,</hi> Iſa. 10 1, 2. So the princes of <hi>Judah</hi> are ſaid <hi>to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, and companions of thieves</hi> (and to ſhew wherein, it is add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) <hi>every one loveth gifts, and followeth after rewards, they judg not the fatherleſs,</hi> Iſa. 1. 23. And ſo generally herein may be inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the going beyond, or defrauding another in any matter, of which we are warned, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. 6. And more particularly, the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52825:24"/>
detaining the wages of him that is hired, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19. 13. Or grinding the faces of the poor in beating them down folow for their work that they cannot ſubſiſt, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 5. which is lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as good husbandry, and juſtified by men; and oh that it were not uſed, and juſtified by believers: And ſelling too dear, and buying too cheap, and uſing extortion in taking exceſſive gain, and increaſe, and uſing falſe weights, and meaſures, <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ephah</hi> (or meaſures) <hi>ſmall, and the ſhekel</hi> (or price) <hi>great, and falſifying the ballances by deceit that they may buy the poor for ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and the needy for a pair of ſhooes, and ſell the refu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the wheat, all which are abominable, and provoking to God,</hi> Amos 8. 4-7. All theſe, and the like to theſe things are the fruit of this evil root. So it is ſaid of thoſe that practiſe evil becauſe it is in the power of their hands; <hi>they covet fields, and</hi> (from thence) <hi>take them by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſo they oppreſs a man and his houſe,</hi> Mica. 2. 2. So it is ſaid of <hi>Jehoiakim; Thine eyes and thine heart are not but for thy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, and for oppreſſion, and for violence to do it,</hi> Jer. 22. 17. Hence covetous and extortioners are joyned together, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. And thieves and covetous, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 10. Yea this leads actually to ſteal, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7. 11. 21. And this ſtealing and extortion is a direct fruit of it.</p>
            <p>5. Yea it leads men to bear falſe witneſs againſt their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, and ſo to take away their good names from them, yea and many times their lives alſo, when this preſent world is loved, and the things thereof promiſed, or men have hope, and aſſurance to inrich themſelves thereby, or to ſecure what they have, how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, for this cauſe, do falſe witneſſes riſe up againſt men, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the congregation of God's poor; and lay to their charge things that they knew not. Hence the perſons who are deſcribed to be covetous, are ſaid <hi>to be falſe accuſers,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 2, 3. Hence the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> when he exhorts the ſouldiers to accuſe no man falſly, he adds, <hi>and be content with your wages,</hi> otherwiſe having their converſation with covetouſneſs, it would lead them to bring falſe accuſation againſt men, <hi>Luk.</hi> 3. 14. This idolatry of covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was that (it may ſeem) which cauſed <hi>Doeg</hi> to deviſe miſchief like a razour, and lye, and bear falſe witneſs againſt the prieſts of the Lord, which procured their being cut off, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52. 2-7.</p>
            <p>6. And the laſt commandment is that we have been ſhewing to be the root of all evil, and an immediate fruit of loving the world, effected by liſtening to, and walking after the carnal mind, and wiſdom of the fleſh, as we have before ſeen.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:52825:25"/>
               <hi>Demon.</hi> 3. Though this iniquity deprives and bereaves the ſoul of good, and is the root of all evil, yet it is a well favour'd ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity (as <hi>Nah.</hi> 3. 4.) and that which is in great requeſt amongſt men; many of the evils it leads to, and of which it is the root, are ſhameful amongſt men, and ſuch as they wil not ſeriouſly plead for, or ſeek to juſtifie though they may walk in them, and ſerve them, until they have ſo long hardened their hearts againſt the inſtructions of wiſdom, and it's reproofs, that they are become paſt feeling, and ſo commit all manner of filthineſs with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſuch as murder, adultery, drunkenneſs, &amp;c. But now this affection, and luſt of the fleſh, this covetouſneſs is in great repute amongſt men; and the labouring to be rich, and laying up for our ſelves here on earth which is included in it, is that for which men will commend us; <hi>When thou doeſt well to thy ſelf, men will praiſe thee,</hi> Pſal. 49. 18. This is that which is highly eſteem'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men (as our Saviour may ſignifie in that expreſſion, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 14, 15.) though yet it is an abomination in the fight of God. And though all luſts are called <hi>the luſts of the fleſh,</hi> both becauſe they ſpring from the carnal mind, or wiſdom of the fleſh; and becauſe they are contrary to the ſpirit, and the luſt thereof; yet when the Apoſtle diſtinguiſhes, and branches them forth, he calls ſome <hi>the deſires of the fleſh,</hi> as ſurfetting, drunkeneſs, adultery, &amp;c. And ſome the deſires of the mind, and under this head of luſts this iniquity is contained, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 3. And therefore <hi>is called the luſt of the eye,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 16. Not onely, nor ſo much of the outward eye, though that alſo may conduce thereto, and affect the heart, but of the eye of the ſoul, and ſo of the mind, becauſe this ſprings from that, and is more ſuited to the wiſdom, and underſtanding of men, as corrupted by the poyſon of Satans temptation, which leads them to think that riches are very excellent, and will render us happy in the injoyment of them; hence we are admoniſhed to ceaſe from our own wiſdom, that we may not labor to be rich (as before) <hi>Pro.</hi> 23. 4. Now then the more appearance of wiſdom there is in it, the more highly will men eſteem it, for vain man would be (and be accounted) wiſe; though he be born like a wild aſſes colt, <hi>Job.</hi> 11. 12. And alſo, as this iniquity being a deſire of the mind is therefore well accounted of amongſt men, ſo in ſerving of it, and laboring to be rich, eſpecially if men find the life of their hands, and that they luſt after, and labor for in any abundance, together herewith they meet with other deſires of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52825:25"/>
mind, which the underſtanding of a man leads him to ſeek after, and highly to prize in the injoyment; theſe being uſually conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitants of this iniquity; As to ſay, the wiſdom of this world (which is ſcience falſly ſo called, and onely ſeeming wiſdom) this alſo is a deſire of the mind, and that men thirſt after; now the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous man, being rich alſo, ſeldom wants the repute of a wiſe man amongſt men, if he have but any conſiderable parts, either natural, or acquired; his being rich gaines him the eſteem of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wiſe, when the wiſdom of the poor is deſpiſed, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9. 16. And however <hi>he is wiſe in his own conceit,</hi> Pro 28. 11. Yea and hereby he hath greater advantage alſo, by accompanying himſelf with great ones, and ſuch as are in repute for wiſdom, whoſe crown in their riches, <hi>Pro.</hi> 14. 24. and otherwiſe to ſeek after the ſatisfying this deſire of the mind. And ſo honor in this world, and the praiſe of men, is a deſire of the mind, and who, like the covetous rich man, is counted worthy of this; men bleſs the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, and every o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bows before them, and the poor uſe intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to them (while they anſwer roughly)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and are even ſervants to them, <hi>Pro.</hi> 18. 23. and 22. 7. riches and honor uſually go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And ſo the friendſhip of this world is a deſire of the mind, and that which men think adds much to their happineſs, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity; and therefore they deſire to have many joyned to them in ſome ſtrict tye of affection, and to ſay a confederacy with them, and therefore to match into, and be allied unto great families, and perſonages, that they may take deep root in the earth; Now wealth maketh many friends, and every one is a lover of him that hath it; <hi>the poor is hated of his neighbor, but many are the lovers of the rich,</hi> Pro: 14. 20. and 19. 4. and hence becauſe there is ſuch a meeting together of other deſires of the mind in the object of this luſt, therefore it is ſo amiable in the eyes of men, and men are ſo purſuing this iniquity with great greedineſs, for in finding the object of this luſt, they ſhall have the friendſhip of this world, praiſe of men, and honor amongſt men; be accounted wiſe, and well accompliſht perſons, and what not.</p>
            <p>Yea, and not onely is this luſt ſo well thought of amongſt men generally; but the Saints of the world alſo are ſecretly purſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and magnifying it, becauſe it will conſiſt, and ſtand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with an appearance of devotion, godlineſs, and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo more groſs luſts which this leads to, will not. Men may ſeek to eſtabliſh a righteouſneſs to themſelves, which is alſo a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52825:26"/>
deſire of the mind, and yet be given to covetouſneſs; yea and be eſteemed religious by others, while yet they are greatly pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with this iniquity. Hence our Savior ſaith of the Phariſees, <hi>that they were covetous:</hi> (and therefore they derided him when he ſaid, <hi>no ſervant can ſerve two Maſters, God, and Mammon;</hi> as think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this was a fooliſh aſſertion of our Savior, and that both might ſtand together well enough<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) <hi>Luk.</hi> 16, 13, 14. And yet they were the ſtraiteſt Sect of the religion of the Jews, <hi>Act.</hi> 26. 5. and were frequent in faſting, and prayer, (exceeding herein, it may ſeem, Chriſt's diſciples, <hi>Luk.</hi> 5. 33.) they kept the Sabbaths, and were zealous in, and for the obſervance of them (and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned our Savior as being one that did not keep them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. 16.) and frequented Synagogues, and appeared righteous before men, being like whited ſepulchres that appear beautifull out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly; their covetouſneſs did ſtand with this ſhew of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo as they appeared righteous unto men; though within they were full of hypocriſie, and iniquity, yet this tooke not away their eſteem among the people, <hi>Math. 23. 25-28. Yea though they devoured widdows houſes, yet for a pretence they made long prayers, Math.</hi> 23. 14. and ſo might be thought in their thus ſwallowing up the poor to do it onely in piety, and godlineſs, and that the Church might be honor'd, and provided for, and this diſpoſed to pious uſes, as alſo they pretended when they honor'd not their parents, as is ſaid. <hi>Math.</hi> 15. 4-6. ſo the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>That in the laſt days perillous times ſhould come; For men ſhould have a form of Godlineſs, and deny the power thereof,</hi> namely, either deny the myſtery of Godlineſs, that God was manifeſt in the fleſh; and ſo deny Jeſus to be the Chriſt; or deny the preaching of the Croſs in the words which the Holy Ghoſt hath taught it: or elſe deny the force, and efficacy of it upon them, and receive not the love of the truth ſo as to be ſaved thereby; now of theſe he ſaith, <hi>they are lovers of their own ſelves, covetous, 2 Tim</hi>-3. 2. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they minded earthly things, and yet had a form of Godlineſs. And according as was foretold by the Apoſtle, ſo doubtleſs it is in our days; many that appear very zealous, and religious perſons, and that do, as the Phariſees did, eſteem themſelves better than others; yet their heart goes after their covetouſneſs; and theſe new Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees fill up, if not exceed, the meaſure of their Fathers; evil men, and ſeducers waxing worſe, and worſe, as was foretold; and ſuch ſuppoſe gain to be Godlineſs; namely, the ſeeking after
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52825:26"/>
that, and what conduces thereto, to be a right, and ſtrait worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 5. and thus it was in former times, thoſe who were given to this iniquity were well ſpoken of, and cryed up, and followed, while the true Prophets were hated, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted. Compare <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. 26. with <hi>Jer.</hi> 8. 8-10. and 6. 13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. 10. 11. Yea and as this iniquity conſiſts with a form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo alſo it leads men, yea and the leaders alſo who are given to it, to cry peace, peace, to them who are guilty of it, and to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them as if they were in a ſafe condition, and that their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs is nothing elſe but a provident care, and circumſpection, and looking after the main, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. 5, 6. and their laying up for themſelves treaſures on earth is nothing but their duty, &amp; provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for their families, which whoſo doth not is worſe than an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del; and ſo men are ſtrengthned in their wickedneſs, that none that liſten to them, return from their iniquity, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6. 13, 14. and 8, 8-11. Yea and by means of the former conſiderations it appeares, that it is a very hidden iniquity, it is ſo cover'd over either with a cloak of Godlineſs, as it was with the Phariſees, <hi>Math.</hi> 15. 4-6. and 23. 14. or with a cloak of righteouſneſs, and honeſty, as with men generally, that it is a very difficult thing to diſcern, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it; it ſo ſeeks to ſhroud it ſelf under Godlineſs, and honeſty, to both which it is an enemy (as before) that untill it break forth into many of its fruits, or ſome groſs ones, it's very hard ſo to ſee it, as to faſten a reproof on it; and ſo much the Apoſtle may ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify, when he ſaith: <hi>Neither uſed we at any time flattering words, as ye know;</hi> (they might be competent judges of that,) <hi>Nor a cloak of covetouſneſs, God is witneſs;</hi> (here he appeals not to them, for this might have been ſo hidden, they might not have diſcerned it, but to God which trieth the heart, who onely knows the truth of it, and diſcovers it by his word which is quick and powerfull, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4 12, 13.) 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 5.</p>
            <p>Now then by how much the more this iniquity is ſo highly eſteemed of amongſt men, and ſuch an one as in which other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the mind are infolded, and ſo exceeding grateful: Yea and it ſo conſiſting with a form of Godlineſs alſo, and being ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally inclined unto, and ſerved by the Saints of the world, and they ready to cry peace, peace, to thoſe that are polluted with it; and having ſuch a large, and comely cloak to cover it ſelf with, that it can hardly be diſcern'd by ſo much the more we have all the greater need to be admoniſhed to take heed, and beware of it;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52825:27"/>
it being ſuch a well favoured iniquity in the eyes of men, and of thoſe that ſeem religious alſo. And as thoſe ſeducers that come to corrupt from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt are the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, the more ſpecious they are in the outſide of them, and therefore are we ſo often admoniſhed of them, <hi>Math. 7. 14. 2 Cor.</hi> 11. 12-15. ſo theſe iniquities that are ſo cloſely covered over with other names, and look't upon as vertues, and ſo highly eſteemed amongſt men, are therefore the more carefully to be avoided by us, leſt we deceive our own ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Demon.</hi> 4. The diſciples of Chriſt need to be admoniſhed of this iniquity alſo, becauſe how ever ſpecious it is amongſt men, yet it is an abomination in the ſight of God, and doth greatly provoke his wrath, and for ſerving this iniquity, the wrath of God cometh upon the children of diſobedience, namely, it comes continually upon them, while men continue it it, and are not waſhed from it, <hi>Eph. 5. 5. Col. 3. 5. For the iniquity of his covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was I wroth, and ſmote him, ſaith the high, and holy one, Iſa.</hi> 57. 17. And ſo</p>
            <p>1. He is wroth for this, and ſmites with the rod of his mouth, <hi>Pſal. 110. 2. Iſa.</hi> 11. 4. even with reproofes, and ſharp rebukes in his word, and the faithfull declaration thereof; He will reprove them, and ſet their iniquity in order before them, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 21. So as even to wound them, and gall their ſpirits; and ſo he is ſaid to hew by his Prophets, to ſlay with the words of his mouth, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6 5. and though this be to a gracious end, as are all his doings while called to day, yet it is an effect of his wrath, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, for mens holding faſt deceit, and refuſing to return; and very grievous to him that forſaketh the way, <hi>Pro.</hi> 15. 10. The word of God (in it's reproving, and diſcovering efficacy) is quick, and powerful, and ſharper than a two-edged ſword, <hi>Heb</hi> 4. 12. it even wound; the ſpirit of a man, when he ſeals home his rebukes in ſharpneſs upon any one, ſo as he onely can heal it again, by creating the fruit of his lips in his Teſtimony, peace, peace, <hi>&amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 57. 18, 19. when he chides, and chides ſharply, he even breaks the heart, that he may open mens ears to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline; though he is ſlow to anger, and therefore to chide; and plenteous in mercy, and therefore will not always chide, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain anger for ever, but revive the heart of the contrite ones, that the ſpirit may not fail before him, <hi>Pſal. 103. 8, 9. Iſa.</hi> 57. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:52825:27"/>2. And if mens uncircumciſed hearts are not humbled, and they turn not at his reproofs, he will ſtill, and further ſmite with his hand, or order great teſtimonies of diſpleaſure, and that in laying afflictions upon men, yea and upon nations, for being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to, and ſerving this iniquity; and ſtill it is more provoking in his peculiar people, his pleaſant plant, that they ſhould defile themſelves herewith; hence believers are admoniſhed with ſuch an one as is called a brother, and is covetous, not to eat; and yet they might eat with a covetous one of this world, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10, 11. on ſuch ſtill his wrath comes, in laying afflictions upon their loyns, and even withdrawing or withholding his manifeſted nighneſs, and the light of his countenance from them, and ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſtill, and further to them, wrath with their ſickneſs; <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5. 17. and ſo he hides him and is wroth; and this is a great aggravation of mens afflictions, of theirs eſpecially, who know how ſatisfying, and reviving the light of his countenance is, <hi>Iſa. 57. 17. Pſal.</hi> 10. 1. Yea by continuing herein, he may be provok't to order, and ſend furious rebukes upon thoſe nations on whom his name is called; ſuch as ſword, famine, peſtilence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo the Prophet ſaith, <hi>I am full of the fury of the Lord, I am weary with holding it in, I will poure it upon the children abroad,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and their houſes ſhall be turned to others with their fields,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For I will ſtretch out my hand upon the inhabitants of the land, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Why ſo? <hi>for from the leaſt of them even to the greateſt of them, every one is given to covetouſneſs, Jer.</hi> 6. 11-13. &amp;c. <hi>and</hi> 8. 10-13. He would recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe their way upon their heads in thoſe judgements; As they had been keeping all for themſelves; ſo he would give it all into the hand of their enemies, and as they had not ſerved the Lord in the abundance of all things; ſo now they ſhould ſerve their enemies in the want of all things, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. 47, 48. Yea for this and the direct fruits of it he permits, and orders them to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by thoſe that are over them, <hi>Mica.</hi> 2. 1-4. and 3. 1-4. Yea for this he may be provok't, and will take away his Prophets, righteous, and merciful ones, and turn the ſongs of the Temple into howlings, ſend a famine, even of hearing the words of the Lord, and though men faſt, and pray, not hear, but cover himſelf with a cloud that their prayer ſhould not paſs through, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 1, 17. with c. 58. 3, 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and 59. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Ezek. 33. 31-33 Amos. 8 3-12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mica.</hi> 2. 1, 2-6. and therein write mens ſin upon their puniſhment, that as they have not dealt their bread to the hungry, nor given
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52825:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
drink to the thirſty, ſo he will withhold the bread of life from them, &amp; the fair Virgins, &amp; yong men ſhall faint for thirſt, <hi>Am.</hi> 8. 11-13. Yea in following after this, he may permit ſome to fall into ſuch fruits of it as to be cut off untimely, and be puniſhed by the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and dye ſhameful deaths in the open ſight of others for their admonition, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7. 21-25. and yet be ſo puniſhed in this world, as to have all their puniſhment here, that they may not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned hereafter. Yea his wrath may ſo come upon men for perſiſting herein againſt the light, and admonitions of his grace, as to give them up to a reprobate mind, to do thoſe things that are not convenient, becauſe they have been filled with all unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, covetouſneſs; <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 28, 29. to worſhip the beaſt who opens his mouth in blaſphemies againſt God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 8. to finiſh iniquity, and ſo fall into deſperation, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 18. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the day of the Lord ſhall come on all them that dwell on the earth as a ſnare, eitheir in particularly taking them away by death, as it did upon this man, who aſſured himſelf of much reſt, &amp; happineſs, and that he was laid in many years; <hi>thou fool, ſaith God, this night ſhall thy ſoul be taken from thee, Luk.</hi> 12. 20-21. or how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever generally when God ſhall ſend us Jeſus again, to deſtroy them that deſtroy the Earth; then the inhabiters of the Earth ſhall be taken in the ſnare, and they ſhall not eſcape, <hi>Iſa. 24. 17, 18. Luk. 21. 34, 35. 1 Theſ.</hi> 5. 3.</p>
            <p>3. And further, and for ever the wrath of God ſhall come, and cometh upon ſuch as abide herein, and are not waſhed in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the ſpirit of our God; <hi>no covetous man, who is an idolater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath any inheritance in the Kingdom of Chriſt, and of God, Eph.</hi> 5. 5. no ſuch an one, as ſuch, and unleſs his name be changed in Heaven, ſhall inherit the Kingdom of Heaven, 1 <hi>Cor. 6. 10. But they drink of the wrath of God which will be poured out with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mixture into the Cup of his Indignation, and ſhall be tormented with fire, and brimſtone in the preſence of the Holy Angels, and of the Lamb, Rev.</hi> 14. 6-11. they are now numbred with, and reckon'd amongſt Idolaters, Adulterers, effeminate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea covetouſneſs is the root of theſe, as is in part ſhewn, and they ſhall have their portion with them in Hell fire, where their worm dyeth not, and their fire is not quenched; Oh that we may not deceive our ſelves, but know, that now God abhorres the covetous, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. 3. and will hereafter in flaming fire take vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus; now
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52825:28"/>
conſider this ye that forget God, leſt he tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver.</p>
            <p>Having thus according to my weakneſs ſpoken to the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, I ſhall adde ſomewhat by way of uſefulneſs. And ſo</p>
            <p>1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> From what hath been ſaid in ſhewing the evil, and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nature, and bitter fruit of this iniquity, I have in ſome meaſure been made ſenſible of my need of crying to God, with the Prophet, who, after he had ſaid, <hi>O Lord the hope of Iſrael, all that forſake thee ſhall periſh, and they that depart from me, ſhall be written in the Earth</hi> (where their hearts have been) <hi>becauſe they have forſaken the Lord the Fountaine of living waters;</hi> adds, <hi>Heal me, O Lord, and I ſhall be healed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 13, 14. it may ſeem, he was made ſenſible of his own miſcarriage, and that he needed Gods mercy in forgiving, and cleanſing him; or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he might have been reputed guilty of the like tranſgreſſion; which procures ſuch wrath: or as the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> when he had been imprecating, and propheſying, that ſuch ſhould be aſhamed which tranſgreſs without cauſe; cryes out to God; <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, O Lord, thy tender mercies,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>remember not the ſins of my youth, nor my tranſgreſſions, but according to thy mercy remember thou me, for thy goodneſs ſake; Pſal.</hi> 25, 3-7. as ſignifying that if God had markt iniquities againſt him, he could not ſtand as juſtified before him; ſo may I ſay alſo; For thy names ſake par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don mine iniquity (of this nature) for it is great; hide away thy face from my ſins (which have ſprung from this root) and blot out all my tranſgreſſions; <hi>create in me a clean heart, O God, and renew a right ſpirit within me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. In that this iniquity is ſo exceeding ſinful, and provoking; it may ſhew unto us, that what is highly eſteem'd among men is an abomination in the fight of God; <hi>for the wiſdom of this world is fooliſhneſs with him;</hi> this will lead to account leſſer ſins to be great ones; and thoſe which are very dangerous to be but ſmall ones, if not vertues: Men have generally an high eſteem of the deſires of the mind (as before is ſhewn) of the wiſdom, riches, honors of this world, and praiſe of men; and eſtabliſhing a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to themſelves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As if theſe might be ſought after commendably; yea, and they are in requeſt amongſt appearing zealous ones, and oh that God's pleaſant plant were not too much polluted with theſe; and particularly with this covetouſneſs, and ſo bring forth fruit to themſelves, in ſetting their affections on
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52825:29"/>
things below, and coveting greedily after more, that they may lay up here on earth for themſelves, and theirs; and ſo withhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from their poor bretheren, and ſomtimes by their cruelty oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioning, and haſtening the death of ſome; ſurely ſuch is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſs of ſin, and eſpecially of theſe deſires of the mind, which the judgment, and wiſdom of a man, as it defiled, leads him to ſeek after, that it would perſwade us, that it is nothing to ſerve ſuch an inclination: Yea many that hate the fruit of this iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, love the root, and perſwade themſelves there is little, or no hurt in it; They think indeed drunkenneſs, uncleanneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable, as indeed they are; but covetouſneſs is but a little moat: like the ſcribes, and Phariſees, thoſe fooliſh, and blind guids, who ſaid, <hi>whoſoever ſhall ſwear by the temple, it is nothing, but whoſoever ſhall ſwear by the gold of the temple, he is a debter,</hi> &amp;c. Math. 23. 16-19. lightly eſteeming the greateſt evils, and pronouncing them guilty that committed the leſs; ſo how many Phariſaical perſons are there that are ſo appearingly holy, that if others in following this root of iniquity have fallen into ſome of the groſs luſts of the fleſh, as Adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Oh how do they abominate thoſe groſs evils, and can hardly come to ſee perſons polluted herewith, leſt they ſhould be defiled, and yet as much given to covetouſneſs as the former: they can ſay, with the Phariſee, <hi>God we thank thee, we are not as others, adulterers,</hi> &amp;c. and yet be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this, which is as, and more dangerous, Compare <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. 11. with 16. 14. they can ſeverely condemn leſſer ſins (as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>David</hi> did, when <hi>Nathan</hi> uſed the Parable to him) and yet be guilty of greater themſelves, and take no notice thereof, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 17. Oh the deceitfulneſs of man's heart!</p>
            <p>3. Seeing covetouſneſs is ſuch an evil, and bitter thing, let us examine our ſelves, and ſearch, and try our hearts, and wayes in the glaſs of the law of liberty; <hi>He that doth truth cometh to the light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt;</hi> therein let us ſcearch our ſelves.</p>
            <p>If any ſhould ſay, God, I thank thee I am not guilty of it, for it is the root of all evil, and I am not guilty of fornication, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, or of ſuch, and ſuch groſs evils, as others are, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore need not this admonition, To ſuch an one I would ſay</p>
            <p>1. That though it be, as indeed it is the root of all evil, yet it ſo appears not, or brings not forth all it's evil fruits in every one that is highly guilty of it; The Phariſees were covetous, and derided
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52825:29"/>
our Savior for ſaying, <hi>no man can ſerve two maſters,</hi> and yet they might not commit open, and groſs idolatry, nor are they taxed with it, nor reproved for it, though that alſo is the fruit of it; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law a man might have the leproſy, and yet not have all the ſignes of it, for they were divers, <hi>Lev.</hi> 13. For though a mans heart goes after his covetouſneſs, yet he may not be ſtrongly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to ſome of it's fruits, nor be under the power of intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to ſome evils, as others may be; and ſin, and Satan uſually ſets upon us where we are weakeſt.</p>
            <p>2. I may ſay to ſuch an one, as the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> doth; <hi>He that ſaid, do not commit adultery, ſaid alſo, do not kill; now if thou commit no adultery, yet if thou kill, thou art become a tranſgreſſour, and ſo mayſt be deeply guilty of this iniquity,</hi> Jam. 2. 11. haſt not thou who thus juſtifieſt thy ſelf, deſpiſed the poor, and in aſſemblies bid them ſtand there, or diſreſpected them? this is murder, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 1-10. Haſt not thou out of love to the things of this preſent world, forborn to feed the hungry, and cloath the naked, when thou hadſt it in the power of thine hand to do it, and on ſight of thy brothers needs haſt had the bowels of thy compaſſion opened? this the charge againſt thoſe on Chriſts left hand, and who ſhall go into everlaſting fire, <hi>Math.</hi> 25. 41. 46. haſt thou not out of love to the things of this world conſumed what thou hadſt put into thine hand upon thy luſts, in pampering thy ſelf, and faring de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly every day, and ſo received, and injoy'd thy good things, and thy poor brother mean time received his evil? This the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the rich man in the Parable which our Savior ſpeak after the affirming the Phariſees were covetous, and his reproving them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. haſt thou not been angry with thy brother, (yea and with the light alſo) when he hath been faithfully reproving, and admoniſhing thee of this evil, and counted them moſt thy friends, who have hated thee, &amp; not rebuk't thee; and ſecretly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the faithful reprovers, and ſpake againſt him; and <hi>He that hateth his brother is a manſlayer,</hi> 1 Joh. 3. 15-18. Ezek. 33. 30-32. hath not the end of thy labor been to inrich thy ſelf, and to lay up treaſures here on earth, and not to give to him that needeth? and when thou haſt found the life of thine hand haſt thou not been ſecretly rejoycing therein, and lifting up thy ſelf above thy poor brethren, yea and departing from the Lord, and from the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of God's people; for fear of being taken, and looſing all? haſt thou not when a ſpecial opportunity hath been put into thine
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:52825:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hand for getting ſilver, and a choice advantage at the ſame time given thee for getting wiſdom, thought there was a neceſſity to imbrace the former, though with a neglect of the latter? haſt thou not in giving given ſparingly, and grudgingly, and ſo as of covetouſneſs, and minded another, and walkt by his example, when he might give according to ability, and though thou hadſt much more in thine hand, yet wouldeſt do but as he did, as one afraid to exceed, and as if thou hadſt parted with thy life when thou gaveſt any thing? in thus diligently ſearching in the light of the glorious Goſpel, thou mayeſt ſee how little reaſon thou haſt to acquit thy ſelfe, yea that thou haſt cauſe enough to ſay <hi>God be merciful to me a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. To ſuch a boaſter I might further ſay, that God might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thee from thus ſinning, and not ſuffer thee to touch another (as <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. 6.) and ſo it might be, not ſo much thy intigrity as effected by the grace of God received, and retained in the midſt of thine heart, which wrought in thee an hatred, and abhorrence of this iniquity thou cleareſt thy ſelf of; as a being forcibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained therefrom, or prevented by God in his providences, when thou hadſt had inclination enough thereto in following thy covetouſneſs; Thou knoweſt, it may be, and art privy to the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of thine heart in often luſting after ſome one forbidden of God; for filthy lucres ſake, and ſo haſt committed adultery in thy heart, though thou haſt not actually had ſuch unclean fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with ſuch an one; it may be with thee in this caſe, as it was with <hi>David</hi> in another; he did purpoſe and was reſolved to have avenged himſelf, but God withheld him, and kept him from ſhedding blood, and avenging himſelf; and this he thankfully acknowledges; not by clearing himſelf as having no intention ſo to do, but in confeſſing his raſhneſs, and ſo giving glory to God; 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 26-34. Yea or I might ſay, that thou haſt been ſtrongly inclined to uncleanneſs by thy love of money, yet other luſts warring in thy members have kept thee from bringing forth this fruit of it; As thou mayeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> together with being covetous, greatly deſireous of vain glory, and loving the praiſe of men, and afraid of ſhame; or thou mayſt have been kept back by fear of puniſhments; and then little reaſon to boaſt herein, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 1.</p>
            <p>4. To ſuch an one I ſhall onely further adde (if this ſin have not left the party thus pleading) that though thou haſt purſued this iniquity of covetouſneſs, and haſt not been guilty of the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52825:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the fleſh hitherto; Yet be not high-minded, but fear; For in following thy covetous inclination, thou mayſt proceed from evil to evil, and at laſt commit, and provoke God to leave thee to the committing that which now thou mayſt loath; <hi>Judas</hi> was a thief ſome time before he indeavour'd to betray his Maſter: And <hi>Hazael</hi> could ſay at one time, is thy ſervant a dogg that he ſhould do great thing? as one greatly abominating it, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it would render him moſt vile; and yet afterwards he did what formerly he ſeemed ſo much to loath, 2. <hi>King. 8. 13, 14. 1 Sam.</hi> 28. 8, 9. Thou mayſt not yet have been tried with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and thirſt, and want, and ſtraits, as another, or been ſo ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tempted to uncleanneſs, in many reſpects, and what theſe if ordered to thee, would occaſion, while thou art inclined to thy covetouſneſs, thou knoweſt not; and therefore though at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thou art not guilty; Yea, though through the grace of God thou art convinced of the evil, and provoking nature of adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet it is a bleſſed thing to fear always, and to be jealous of thy ſelf, that thou maiſt be tempted, and overcome of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation when tempted, as others have been; <hi>Agur</hi> was an holy man, and yet as one ſenſible of his readineſs to halt, when tried, ſaith, and prays; <hi>Give me neither poverty, nor riches,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>leſt</hi> (on the one hand) <hi>I be full, and deny thee, and ſay who is the Lord</hi> (as <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh, Exod.</hi> 5. 2.) or (on the other) <hi>leſt I be poor, and ſteal, and take the name of my God in vain</hi> (in walking in uncleanneſs, or any evil luſt for providing for himſelf.) <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 7-9. Oh were we but alike ſenſible of our own vileneſs, and readineſs to halt, when tried; we ſhould be more jealous of our ſelves, and if this iniquity of covetouſneſs be in our hands put it farre away; and this leads to another uſe.</p>
            <p>4. Seeing this covetouſneſs is ſo hurtful, deceitful, and provok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an evil; Let us all be warned to take heed, and beware of it, that our hearts be not inclined hereto; yea pray to him who is able to ſave us, that he would incline our hearts to his teſtimonies, and not to covetouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 119. 36, 37. This admonition is here by our Savior given generally to a great multitude, and to his diſciples, &amp; it is proper to be given in, and with the Goſpel to all that hear the word; and therefore meet to be received by all: ſome admonitions may not properly be given to all, becauſe they are not capable of offending in ſuch caſes; As, not to truſt in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain riches, which is included in this iniquity, or which this
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52825:31"/>
leads to, is given to the rich in this world; but to the poor it cannot ſo properly be given, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 17. &amp; ſo ſome may not need to be warned to take heed of actual adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For they may be ſo weakned, as that that ſin may have left them; or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe made incapable; but now any perſon may be inclined to covetouſneſs, from the leaſt to the greateſt; from the yongeſt who have the uſe of underſtanding, to the oldeſt; from the pooreſt to the richeſt; and let none think, that becauſe of any attaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they may ſleight this warning; For the Holy Ghoſt gives it to all that are in Chriſt, not onely to little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and young men, but to Fathers alſo, and ſo to the moſt experienced believers, and who have been inſtruments of beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting others through the Goſpel; To them all is this admonition given, <hi>love not the world, nor the things in the world; if any man love the world, the love of the Father is not him, 1 Joh.</hi> 2. 12-15. Oh let us not murmure here againſt; but be thankful that we may through his grace receive it, and take heed, &amp; beware of it; and that we may do ſo, follows to be ſhewed in the next inſtruction, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. That they that hear the word may take heed, and beware of covetouſneſs, in the light, and ſtrength of God's grace.</p>
            <p>So much is ſignified in this admonition given by our Savior, for he looks not to reap where he hath not ſown, though wicked ſervants ſo charge him, <hi>Math. 25 24-26. his yoke is eaſie, and his bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den light, &amp; his commandments are not grievous, Math. 11. 30. 1 Joh.</hi> 5 3. &amp; therefore he doth not onely warn of what is evil, but he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents men with the light, and power of his grace in due time, that men might ariſe from dead things; The grace of God doth not ſimply teach men to deny ungodlineſs, but that men might receive &amp; obey it's teachings, it ſeaſonably brings ſalvation to all men (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in this appearance of it, in which it is more brightly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted than formerly) it brings ſome diſcovery of that great ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation wrought, and compleated for us in Chriſt, and therewith ſaving ſtrength alſo, to inable us, <hi>that denying ungodlineſs, and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts, we may live ſoberly,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11, 12. and otherwiſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not flee from what is reproved, for we have no ſufficiency of our ſelves, as of our ſelves to think any thing that is good.</p>
            <p>We ſhall therefore together ſhew, that thoſe that hear the word may take heed of this iniquity; and by what means in general we ſay, <hi>the Goſpel of Chriſt is the power of God to ſalvation to every one that believes, Rom.</hi> 1. 16. the law opens no door of repentance, but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52825:31"/>
ſaith, <hi>curſed is every one that continues not in all things written in the book of the law to do them, Gal.</hi> 3. 10. But now Chriſt hath redeemed us from the curſe of the Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 13. and the declaration here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is the great inſtrument God makes uſe of for delivering us from every path of the deſtroyer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. 4. and 119. 9.</p>
            <p>The Law of the Lord (of or concerning him who is Lord of all) is perfect (compleat, entire) converting the ſoul, both at firſt, and ſo continually, it is converting the ſoul, whether men are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by it, or no, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 7. with this the Apoſtle was ſent to open mens eyes, <hi>and to turn them from darkneſs to light, and from the power of Satan to God; Act.</hi> 26. 17. 18-22. 23. There are in this Goſpel contained great, and glorious arguments that we may be delivered from this preſent evil world, and theſe are powerful to this end, becauſe Chriſt by his ſpirit is preſent therewith even to the end of the world, and ſo with his ſervants in their faithful declaring it, without hidden things of diſhoneſty, ſo that while <hi>Paul</hi> plants, and <hi>Apollo</hi> waters, God ſails not to give increaſe, whether m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n receive it, or no, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 5-7. and they that receive this teſtimony of Jeſus with the heart, and keep it in believing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, ſhall prove it to be the power of God; hence the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith to the Corinthians (who were ſome of them covetous) <hi>ye are waſhed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the ſpirit of our God, 1 Cor. 6. 10, 11. 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 20. and 1. 1. 18, 19.</p>
            <p>Now then to this end that we may take heed, and beware of covetouſneſs, and to ſhew we may do ſo, we ſhall a little particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly conſider what is contained in this teſtimony of Jeſus in each of the three branches for our helpfulneſs; <hi>viz.</hi> in what he hath done, and is become; in what he is now doing, and in what he will do hereafter.</p>
            <p>1. In this Teſtimony of Jeſus in what he hath done, and is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, is ſhewed to us, that Jeſus Chriſt the Word, who was with God, and was God, was made fleſh for ſinful mankind, and laid hold of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Adam,</hi> in that body which the Father prepared for him, whereby his ear was opened, and he fitted to do the will of God, in being further abaſed for us, and doing what was needful to our being brought back to God; in order whereto, he had the treſpaſſes of the world (even the guilt of all thoſe treſpaſſes which occaſioned the firſt breath, and enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty between God, and mankind) imputed to him; <hi>For God made him who knew no ſin, to be ſin for us, 2. Cor.</hi> 5. 19-21. He bare our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:52825:32"/>
ſins in his own body to (and on) the tree, and God therefore went to law with him, <hi>He was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for our iniquites;</hi> he by the grace of God taſted death for every man, <hi>Heb. 2. 9. He was delivered for our offences, and is raiſed again for our juſtification;</hi> and ſuch the vertuouſneſs, and preciouſneſs of his perſonal abaſement, and ſufferings, in the vertues whereof he is taken from priſon, and judgement, that he hath redeemed us in himſelf from the curſe of the law, purged away our ſins from before the preſence of God, ſlain the enmity that was between God and us, taken out of the way all that was contrary to us, aboliſhed our death, and ſpoiled principalities, and powers, and made a ſhew of them openly triumphing over them in himſelf; and ſo hath made peace for us by the blood of his Croſs, <hi>Gal. 3. 13. Iſa. 53. 5, 6. Eph. 2. 14-16. Col. 2. 14, 15. 2 Tim.</hi> 1. 9, 10. And hath recovered, reſtored, and brought back our loſs into himſelf, ſo that there is compleatneſs for us in him; he hath not onely taken away, and removed the guilt of our firſt ſin, and ſinfulneſs from before the preſence of God; but having offered himſelf a ſpotleſs ſacrifice to the Father throug the eternal Spirit hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained power to make reconciliation for the ſins of the people, which are condemnable according to the rule of the glorious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 27. and 2. 17. through this man is preached to us the forgiveneſs of ſins, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 37, 38. and he hath reſtored our nature in himſelf to perfect innocency, integrity, and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and is filled with all the fulneſs of grace, and truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 14-17. and hath obtain'd eternal redemption for us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 12. and confirmed a new Teſtament of great, and precious promiſes of all things that pertain to life, and godlineſs, and an everlaſting covenant, 2 <hi>Cor. 1. 20. Heb.</hi> 13. 20. So that he is become a rich, and full fountain in which there is pardon, peace, righteouſneſs, ſpirit, promiſes, eternal life. 1 <hi>Joh. 5. 10, 11. Yea all things are delivered to him of the Father, Math. 11. 27. all things are here ready a feaſt of fat things prepared for all people, Iſa. 25. 6. All things that the Father hath is his, Joh.</hi> 16. 15. and he in our nature, and for us is glorifyed with the Fathers own ſelf with the glory he had with him before the world was, <hi>Joh. 17. 5. The Father hath ſo loved the Son, becauſe he laid down his life; that he might take it up again, that he hath given all things into his hand, Joh.</hi> 3. 35<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with chap. 10. 17, 18. made him both Lord, and Chriſt, <hi>the laſt Adam, the quickning ſpirit, the Lord, the fountaine of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:52825:32"/>
living waters, wiſedome, righteouſneſs, ſanctification,</hi> and <hi>redemption;</hi> he is beautiful, and glorious, excellent, and comely for our eſcap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; he is the foundation God hath laid in <hi>Zion,</hi> the fountaine of forgiveneſs, grace, and ſpirit; God hath given him glory that our faith, and hope might be in God; and this perfection is in him for every man, and it was the work of the Apoſtles, and is of thoſe that ſo walk as they have them for an enſample to warn eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, and teach every man in all wiſdom, that they may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent every man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus, that they may ſhew all men where compleatneſs is prepared for them, even durable riches, and righteouſneſs, that they may not be at a loſs, or put upon it to ſeek bread, reſt, peace, and feeding in deſolate places, but may know aſſuredly by the light of this Teſtimony, that he is the reſt for the weary, and he the refreſhing, 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 45. Iſa. 4. 2. Col. 1. 28, 29. Iſa.</hi> 28. 12-16.</p>
            <p>Now then in this firſt, great, and fundamental branch of the Goſpel is ſhewed to us that we may take heed and beware of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in General, and ſo of this of covetouſneſs; For in what is ſaid we may ſee and learn</p>
            <p>1. That there is forgiveneſs with him. For</p>
            <p>1. We are not now neceſſarily under the guilt, and dominion of our ſins, for as is ſaid, <hi>he is raiſed for our juſtification, who dyed for our ſins,</hi> and this ſo vertuous that as all have ſinned, and are come ſhort of the glory of God, ſo they are juſtified freely by Gods grace through the redemption that is in Jeſus; and this true before he is ſet forth to be a propitiation through faith in his blood, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 23-25. He hath ſo ſatisfied God's juſtice, fulfilled his truth, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his wrath, anſwered his law, and ſo paid our debt; that now the wrath of God doth not abide on any man ſimply, becauſe our firſt Father hath ſinned, and we in him, or becauſe we are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, and unavoidably polluted, and defiled in our own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as we come to have a being from him, and ſo are neceſſarily inclined to pride, covetouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is not the condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we are by nature, and firſt birth darkneſs; but that light is vouchſafed, and men love darkneſs rather than light, <hi>&amp;c. Joh.</hi> 3. 19. The judgement of this world was executed upon, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered by Jeſus Chriſt, ſo that no man is condemned becauſe he hath ſinned in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> ſimply, and comes forth from him neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily polluted; but there is a door of repentance opened, and all the ends of the Earth called to look to him, and be ſaved, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45. 22.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52825:33"/>
Nor ſhall any man periſh for ever in that firſt death, but be all rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed again by the man Chriſt Jeſus; and ſhall not then be judged according to that firſt rule of judgement, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 22-27. And this, becauſe Jeſus Chriſt by the grace of God taſted death for every man, and is raiſed again from the dead; and indeed other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we are yet in our ſins, and muſt ſo abide for ever (for no man can redeem his brother, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. 7.) and all faith preaching, and hope is in vain, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 14-17. if there were any one man for whom Chriſt hath not by the grace of God taſted death, it were impoſſible for ſuch an one to flee from covetouſneſs, and in vain to warn him ſo to do; The houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were reaſoning rightly, if there had been any ground for their ſo ſaying; <hi>If</hi> (ſay they) <hi>our tranſgreſſions, and our ſins be upon us, and we pine away in them, how can we then live? how can we turn to God from Idols to ſerve the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and true God? it is impoſſible, Ezek.</hi> 33. 10. So may we ſay; if mens ſins be upon them which they are naturally, and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily guilty of, and polluted with, there is then no hope, the caſe is deſperate; But what he ſaid to them when they were ſo reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord, I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turn from his way, and live, Verſ.</hi> 11. is generally true concerning mankind, while he is calling to them; and of the truth of this he hath given his Son for a witneſs, in that he appointed him, and he was manifeſted to take away our ſins, and in him is no ſin, 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 5. As the firſt offence was unto all men to condemnation, ſo the righteouſneſs of the laſt <hi>Adam</hi> was to all men to juſtification of life, in an anſwerable ſenſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he once in the end of the world appeared to put away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 26. and by vertue, and as the effect thereof, he hath delivered us in himſelf from the power of our enemies; <hi>Now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the judgement of this world</hi> (namely when his ſoul was troubled) <hi>now ſhall the Prince of this world be caſt out</hi> (namely, from being the Prince of the world, as he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily according to the curſe of the law,) <hi>And I, if I be lifted up from the Earth, will draw all men unto me,</hi> (namely from under the judgement of the world, and dominion of the Prince of the world) <hi>Joh. 12. 27, 31, 32. Joh. 17. 2. Math.</hi> 12. 28, 29. Now then herein is further evidenced, that man may lay a part all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs, and ſo this of covetouſneſs, in that, that ſnare of Satan is broken, and we are in Chriſt deliver'd, without which we had been neceſſarily bond-ſlaves to him, and led captive by him at his
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:52825:33"/>
pleaſure, being ſhut out, and baniſhed from God; <hi>But he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us in himſelf, out of the hands of our enemies, that we might ſerve him without fear, in righteouſneſs, and holineſs before him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luk. 1. 73-75. Pſal. 98. 1-4. Col. 2. 15. Oh that men would praiſe the Lord for his goodneſs, and for his wonderful works to the children of men; For he hath broken the gates of braſs, and cut the bars of iron in ſunder, Pſal.</hi> 107. 15, 16. He hath broken down the middle wall of partition between God and us; hath taken out of the way all that was in the way contrary to us, nailing it to his Croſs; and having ſpoiled principalities, and powers, he made a ſhew of them openly triumphing over them in himſelf, <hi>Eph. 2. 14, 15. Col. 2. 14, 15. Pſal.</hi> 47. 1-5, 6. and 68. 18.</p>
            <p>2. Herein is alſo ſhewn, that Jeſus Chriſt hath not onely purged away the guilt of that firſt ſin, and ſinfulneſs from before the preſence of God; but alſo that he hath obtained power into himſelf to make reconciliation for the ſins of the people, which they are guilty of upon a new account, and which deſerve new wrath, even the wrath to come; he hath not onely received gifts in the man for men (as they come to have a being from <hi>Adam</hi>) but for the rebellious alſo (that are diſobedient, and gainſaying to the Goſpel, compare <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 2. with <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 21.) that the Lord God might dwell among them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. 18. without which they could not poſſibly be made an habitation for him. He offer'd up ſacrifice, firſt for his own ſins (which were imputed to him, and accepted by him as his to anſwer for) and then for the peoples; and this he did (not often, as the former High-prieſts, he needed not to do it daily, but) once, when he offered up himſelf, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 27. and 10, 11, 12. He hath not onely made peace for us by the blood of his Croſs; But he is our peace, <hi>Eph. 2. 14. the propitiation for the ſins of the whole world,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 2. and the propitiatory, and Mercy-ſeat, and ſo ſet forth in the word of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 25. and as in our types of old, the Mercy-ſeat was put above, and ſo did cover the ark in which was the two tables of the covenant, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our ſinfulneſs, and vileneſs is diſcovered, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. 21, 22. even ſo Jeſus Chriſt he is the true Mercy-ſeat, the covering for our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal ſins, in which we alſo tranſgreſs the law; &amp; for which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we ſhould ſpeedily be cut off; without this alſo we could not lay apart any thing that is evil; For there is no man that ſinneth not, who can ſay he hath made his heart clean, or that he is pure from his iniquity, and ſo particularly from this iniquity of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:52825:34"/>
now were there not this proviſion made for us in, and thorow the blood of Jeſus, were there not forgiveneſs of thoſe ſins in which we ſin againſt the grace of God bringing ſalvation there could be no opportunity for us to come to be waſhed, or to ſeek deliverance therefrom, and ſo God could not be worſhipped by us: <hi>If thou Lord ſhouldſt mark iniquities, O Lord, who ſhall ſtand? but there is forgiveneſs with thee that thou maieſt be feared, Pſal.</hi> 130. 3, 4. Herein the grace of God, &amp; gift by grace doth exceed the firſt offence; <hi>For the judgment was by one</hi> (offence) <hi>to condemnation; but the free gift is of many offences unto juſtification, Rom.</hi> 5. 16. not only to juſtification and diſcharge from that firſt offence, but from many offences in which men ſin after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and in Chriſt God is become a God gracious, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to ſinners, a God of pardon, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. 17. forgiving iniquity, and tranſgreſſion, and ſin; who can righteouſly heal men, and forgive their iniquity of covetouſneſs; whoſe name, and power is great for pardoning great iniquities, <hi>Numb. 14. 17-19. Pſal.</hi> 25. 11. with whom there is plenteous redemption in Chriſt Jeſus, through his blood, the forgiveneſs of ſins, according to the riches of his grace, for thieves, covetous ones, rebellious tranſgreſſours, backſliders, while the day of grace, and patience is continued to them, <hi>Pſal. 130. 7. Eph. 1. 7. 1 Cor.</hi> 6. 10, 11. And alſo through this man, who is raiſed from the dead, and ſaw not corruption, is preached to us the forgiveneſs of our ſins, without ſome diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very whereof, no man could be incouraged in believing to confeſs his ſins, <hi>Act. 13. 37, 38. Pſal. 130. 3, 4. Jer.</hi> 3. 12, 13. 22. and 31. 19. <hi>Joel. 2. 13. Rom. 2. 4. Iſa. 55. 1-6, 7. Act.</hi> 5. 30, 31.</p>
            <p>2. In this firſt, and fundamental branch of the Teſtimony is declared to us the vileneſs of our ſins, which needed ſuch a mighty one to be abaſed for us, as was the Son of God, and the vanity of our idols; for none of theſe could be a meet ſacrifice to be offered up to God; We were not redeemed with corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things, as ſilver, and gold, but with the precious blood of Chriſt; thouſands of rams, and ten thouſand rivers of oyl would not have ſatisfied for the ſin of the World, or have made peace, they profited not in this day of wrath, for if they could, Chriſt hath dyed in vain, 1 <hi>Pet. 1. 18, 19. Gal.</hi> 2. 21. it was neceſſary that he that was in the form of God, ſhould take on him our nature, and become obedient to death; or otherwiſe we muſt have pined away in our iniquities, and have been for ever expelled from the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:52825:34"/>
preſence of God; hence it was the Apoſtles maner, and cuſtom to open, and alleadge, that Chriſt muſt needs have ſuffered, and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen again, <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 3. this then ſhews that we are debters but not to the World, that we ſhould love it, or the things thereof; Was it crucified for us? Or were we baptized into the name of it that we ſhould ſet our hearts, and affections on it? What ingagement hath it laid upon us that we ſhould forſake the Lord, the fountain of living waters, and luſt after, and hew to our ſelves broken ciſterns that can hold no water? hath this redeemed us from the curſe of the law, or did it contribute any thing thereto? Was this the means by which Chriſt made peace for us, or needed he, or poſſeſſed he a great ſhare of this, that he might do the will of God in order to our recovery? look we into, and continue looking into the perfect law of liberty, and this wil be powerful to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us to mortifie our members, which are on the earth. Thus the Apoſtle ſound it; <hi>God forbid that I ſhould glory ſave in the croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, whereby the world is crucified to me,</hi> Gal. 6. 14. it was herein rendred as a dead, vile, unprofitable thing to him, as that in which he could take no delight; in the preaching of this Croſs it appeares, that without bloodſhedding there was no remiſſion to be obtained, no peace to be made but by the blood of his Croſs, no victory to be gotten over our enemies but thorow death; how then ſhall we give our loves unto, or ſet our hearts upon ſuch vain things that have not profited us? And eſpecially how ſhall they that have been baptized into Chriſt, and thereto were baptized into his death (inſtructed, and waſhed into the knowledge thereof, in which they ſee the emptineſs of all idols, and that theſe things are not of the Father, but are of the world, how ſhall they) ſet their affections on things on the earth, or mind earthly things?</p>
            <p>3. In this alſo is ſhewed unto us a rich, and compleat proviſion of all things treaſured up in the perſon of our Jeſus, obtained by his blood, which are infinitely better than what naturally we are deſiring, and that which in the injoyment will give reſt to us; in which alſo he is ſhewing the emptineſs of all other things: For the holy Spirit in glorifying Chriſt, therein ſhewes to us, <hi>that all fleſh is graſs, and the goodlineſs thereof, the glory of man to be as the flower of graſs; the graſs withereth, and the flower thereof falleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; riches are not for ever, but the word of the Lord endureth for ever.</hi> Iſa. 40. 6. 8. 1 Pet. 1. 18-24, 25. Here are exceeding better trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:52825:35"/>
provided for us, and laid up in a ſure hand, and in ſeeking them with the whole heart we ſhall bemade partakers of them: In him are unſearchable riches; <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. 9. All treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge, <hi>Col. 2. 3. riches, and honor are with him, yea durea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble riches, and righteouſneſs,</hi> Pro. 8. 18. in ſeeking after him the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſhall be our gold, and we ſhall have ſilver of ſtrength, <hi>Job. 22. 25. God hath given us</hi> (mankind) <hi>eternal life, and this life is in his Son,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 10, 11. This is that treaſure to be deſired, which is in the dwelling of the wiſe, in the ſecret place of the moſt high, <hi>Pro. 21. 20. The Merchandiſe whereof is better than the Merchandiſe of ſilver, and the gain thereof than fine gold,</hi> &amp;c. Pro. 3. 13. 15. <hi>and 8. 19. How much better is it to get wiſdom than gold?</hi> &amp;c. Pro. 16. 16. <hi>Man knoweth not the price thereof,</hi> Job. 28. 12-20. What would it profit a man if he had the whole world in a day of wrath, would this ſave him? would this procure the forgiveneſs of his ſins? will this give peace, or make a man partaker of the favour of God, and fellowſhip with him? will it obtain his love? no, <hi>if a man would give all the ſubſtance of his houſe for love, it would utterly be contemned,</hi> Cant. 8. 7. Pro. 11. 4. Zeph. 1. 18. their ſilver, and their gold ſhall not be able to deliver in the day of the Lords Wrath; they ſhall not ſatisfie their ſouls, nor fill their bowels, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7. 19. But God hath freely provided better things for us; in which is ſhewn, that thoſe uncertain riches have no glory as compared with the glory of this durable riches in Chriſt, this man who hath made peace for us, and is our peace, is more precious than fine gold, than the golden wedge of Ophir, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13. 12. He is ſo in himſelf, and to them that believe he is precious; this is that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure hid in a field, the which when a man hath found he hideth, and for joy thereof goeth, and ſelleth all that he hath, and buyes that field; counts all as dung, that he may win him, and be found in him, <hi>Math. 13. 44-46. Phil.</hi> 3. 7-9. How powerful would the conſideration hereof be to ingage to ſet our affections on things above, and not on things on the earth, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 1, 2. Conſidering alſo, that as there is ſuch an excellency in thoſe riches which the Lamb hath worthily received, becauſe he was ſlain, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 12. ſo he is poſſeſſed of them for us, even for us mankind; hence all are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon to come to the Waters, even every one that thirſteth; not onely thoſe that are gracious thirſters, and who thirſt after more from the taſtes they have forehad of the graciouſneſs of the Lord; but ſuch alſo as are ſeeking refreſhing where it is not; and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:52825:35"/>
ſo are reproved <hi>for laboring for what is not bread, and ſpending their money for what profits not,</hi> Iſa. 55. 1-6, 7. Yea our Savior on this ground, becauſe all things are delivered to him of the Father in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites all that labor, and are heavy laden to come to him, and he would give them reſt; in which he ſignifies that they were ſuch as had not yet reſt though they labor'd for it; and therefore they were not laboring for it, or ſeeking it where it was, and yet he graciouſly calls them, <hi>Math.</hi> 11. 27, 28. and inſtructs thoſe that were laboring for the meat that periſheth, to labor for that which indures to eternal life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 27. as intimating this meat was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them, and indeed the bread which he gives is his fleſh which he hath given for the life of the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 51. ſo that alſo in ſeeking after this he will give it unto them; <hi>Pro.</hi> 2. 1-6. As he hath obtained all into himſelf that are excellent for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ſo he hath given unto us aſſurance in his great, and precious promiſes confirmed by his blood that every one that asketh ſhall receive, <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 7, 8. and ſuch incouragement he hath not given us, that in laboring to be rich, he will grant our deſire herein; yea in mercy he may ſo diſappoint, and befool us, that we may not find the life of our hands; <hi>But if any lack wiſdom, let him ask it of God who giveth liberally to all men, and upbraids not, and it ſhall be given him,</hi> Jam. 1. 5. were this proviſion in Chriſt never ſo ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, and inriching (as it is infinitely ſo) yet while men are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that it is prepared for them before they come, and whether they come, or no, and ſure to be had in ſeeking after it, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelves with their husks rather than to run at ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty for ſuch things as are not ſeen; &amp; <hi>that meſſage which comes to men by the hand of a fool cutteth off the feet,</hi> Pro. 26. 6. it hinders them, and takes off their affections, and purſuit after the things that are ſo infinitely worthy, and more to be deſired than gold, yea than much fine gold; while fools (who conſent not, or come not up, to wholeſome words, even the words of our Lord and Savior, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 4, 5. and ſo know not whether Chriſt hath dyed for thoſe they declare their meſſage to, or whether God loves them, or there be any better things certainly prepared for them in Chriſt before they ſeek, and whether they ſeek, or no, and ſo, ſure to be had in ſeeking) do yet exhort men to labor to know whether Chriſt dyed for them, to labor for that meat which indureth to eternal life, to get an intereſt in Chriſt, to labor to repent, and turn to God. The things that are not ſeen, though excellent,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:52825:36"/>
yet are ſuch as men naturally have no delight in, or deſire after; and therefore the Holy Ghoſt, not onely commends them to us as thoſe things that are principal, and moſt deſireable; but alſo, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures men that all things are ready for them; the bread is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and wine mingled, <hi>Math. 22. 4 8. Pro. 9. 1-5. Iſa.</hi> 55. 1 4-6. and affirms that thoſe that follow lying vanities forſake their own mercies, looſe their own ſouls, deny the Lord that bought them, <hi>Jona. 2. 8. Math. 16. 26. 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 1. and that in coming to Chriſt, as God is drawing them, they ſhall not be aſhamed of their hope: That ſo men may be incouraged upon principles of certainty, and truth to ſeek the Lord while he may be found: it was the confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that there was bread enough in his Fathers houſe, and to ſpare, that made the Prodigal reſolve to return to him, and no longer expoſe himſelf to periſh with hunger, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. 17, 18. This branch of the Teſtimony of Jeſus the Apoſtle deliver'd firſt of all unto the Corinthians, while they were ſome of them thieves, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, &amp;c. to wit, that Chriſt dyed for their ſins, and was buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and roſe again the third day, &amp;c. to redeem them from this iniquity; and it was powerful, for by it they were ſaved, &amp;c. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 6. 10. 11. with <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. 1-3. Yea</p>
            <p>4. He hath made ſuch proviſion in his great and precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes which are all confirmed in the blood of Chriſt, and ſure to all the ſeed, forgiving to us whatſoever is good for us in, and to to our ſeeking after him, as is powerful, as viewed in the Croſs of Chriſt, to preſerve us from covetouſneſs: Jeſus Chriſt who was for a little while made lower than the Angels, that he might by the grace of God taſte death for every man: is now crowned with glory, and honour; and he hath not onely received all ſpiritual bleſſings in Heavenly things, ſuch as pardon, righteouſneſs, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, eternal life; but God hath given him dominion over the works of his hands, and hath put all things under his feet, though yet we ſee not all things put under him; This was contained in the loſs of the firſt publick man, that having ſinned, he deprived himſelf of the glory of God, and ſo of that dominion which God gave him over the works of his hands; but now Jeſus Chriſt hath reſtored that which he took not away, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. 4-8. with <hi>Heb. 2. 7, 8. The Earth is the Lord Chriſt's, and the fulneſs thereof, Pſal.</hi> 24. 1. with 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 21-26. All power is given to him in Heaven, and in Earth, Math.</hi> 28. 18. Indeed this is not gloriouſly manifeſted now, as it ſhall be hereafter, but we by faith may know that God hath
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:52825:36"/>
put all things under his feet, <hi>Eph. 1. 21, 22. All that the Father hath is his, Joh.</hi> 16. 15. and he, as thus furniſhed, hath given us aſſurance in his promiſes that in ſeeking him we ſhall have of theſe things what he ſees needful, and good for us; which promiſes are ſo ratified, and ſealed by his blood, that there is no reaſon, or room left for us, while walking in the light of the Lord, to call into queſtion his faithfulneſs in performing, ſee how the Holy Ghoſt ſets this before us to preſerve from covetouſneſs, and from the practiſe of thoſe that exerciſe themſelves thereto: Our Savior when he warns his diſciples of taking thought for their life, or body, he gives this inſtruction and promiſe to them, ſeek ye firſt (in, and unto all things) the Kingdom of God, and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and all theſe things (namely, what you ſhall eat, what you ſhall drink, and wherewith you ſhall be cloathed) ſhall be added to you, <hi>Math.</hi> 6. 24-34. ſo the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Let your converſation be without covetouſneſs, and be content with ſuch things as you have (namely as you have, prepared in Chriſt, in whom all things are yours, even the world, life, things preſent,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 21-23. and which you have aſſured to you in his promiſes, and he is giving to you in his way.) For he hath ſaid, <hi>I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee;</hi> ſo that we may boldly ſay, <hi>the Lord is my helper,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Heb. 13. 5, 6. Pſal.</hi> 34 8-10. Behold the eye of the Lord is upon them that fear him, upon them that hope in his mercy, to deliver their ſoul from death, and to keeps them alive in famine, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. 18, 19. ſee alſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 3, 4, 19. and 84. 10, 11.</p>
            <p>He hath not promiſed us meat for our luſt, or that he will give unto us ſuch accommodations as our naturall ſpirit is deſiring, and craving, that may be hurtful for us; but what ever he ſees we need to our ſeeking him he will not withhold. Yea he may bring his people into many ſtraits, ſo that they may be in hunger, and thirſt, in faſtings, in cold, and nakedneſs, for the trial of their faith; and that they may learn to live the life they live in the fleſh by the faith of the Son of God, who loved us, and gave himſelf for us: <hi>But he will cauſe all things to work together for good to them that love God, who are the called according to purpoſe, Rom.</hi> 8. 28-32-37 39. Yea and he that gave his Son in due time to dye for us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly ones, while without ſtrength, will in due time, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably be mindful of his covenant, in giving meat to them that fear him, till they have finiſhed their courſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111. 4, 5. Oh what powerful arguments are contain'd, and what compleat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:52825:37"/>
is given to us in this word of the beginning of Chriſt, to ſtrengthen us to receive this admonition, <hi>viz, To take heed, and beware of covetouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. That men may take heed, and beware of covetouſneſs while called to day, is manifeſt, in what Jeſus Chriſt is now doing in his preſent work, and office whereto the Father hath appointed him; and that both in what he doth to us from Heaven in the name of the Father; and in what he doth for us in Heaven with the Father, in both which he is the Savior of all men, eſpecially of them that believe. And ſo</p>
            <p>1. Jeſus Chriſt who hath made peace for us by his blood, and is our peace; in whom dwelleth the fulneſs of the Godhead bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is appointed, and hereby fitted to be, and is the great Apoſtle by whom God hath ſpoken to us in theſe laſt days, and by whom he ſtill ſpeaketh in his Teſtimony by his Spirit to our ſpirits, that we might know the things freely prepared for us, and given us in himſelf, that through the knowledge of it we might be redeemed from the Earth; he is the great peace-preacher, preventing every man in due time with ſome diſcoveries of his goodneſs; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially us, amongſt whom the Scriptures in the records thereof are preſerved; <hi>He is the true light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world;</hi> and more advantage doth he give to us, upon whom his name is called, in opening our blind eyes in due time, and turning us to God from Idols, and ſo ſaving us from our ſins; For to this end hath God appointed him to be the light, that he might ſave us; for thus he ſaith, <hi>I have given thee for a light of the Gentiles, that</hi> (by this means) <hi>thou ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt be for ſalvation to the ends of the Earth,</hi> Act. 13. 47. <hi>The grace of God that bringeth ſalvation to all men hath appeared, teaching us, that denying ungodlineſs, and worldly luſts, we ſhould live ſoberly,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 11, 12. it brings ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to all men in due ſeaſon, not finds it in men beforehand; and it is ſaving, not onely it hath ſuch a tendency in it, but alſo there is ſaving ſtrength accompanying it, to ſtrengthen men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it in it's appearance, and therewith to deny worldly luſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Otherwiſe how glorious ſoever the things be which Chriſt hath wrought, and obtained into himſelf for us, men cannot take heed, and beware of any thing reproved; <hi>For man is born like a wild Aſſes colt,</hi> the way of peace they know not; they have no wiſdom in them; they cannot know thoſe things which belong to their peace, for they are ſpiritually diſcerned; nor can they ſee the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:52825:37"/>
of covetouſneſs, but may think it to be godlineſs; every man by his knowledge is bruitiſh; and thence they have no free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of will to chuſe life, and refuſe death; no affection to, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire after things that are above; But God hath put his ſpirit upon his Son, and hath given him for a light of the Gentiles, to open the blind eyes, <hi>&amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 42. 1-6. 7. and 49. 6-9. <hi>and good, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right</hi> (faithful to him that appointed him) <hi>is the Lord; therefore will he teach ſinners in the way, Pſal.</hi> 25. 8. ſo that when men are walking in the iniquity of their covetouſneſs to the provoking God to wrath, and to ſmite them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he (to recover them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from) creates the fruits of his lips, peace, peace, to him that is far off, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 17-19. he makes known his words to the worſt of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and particularly to thoſe that are greedy of gain, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with reproving them, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1. 19-23. upon whom doth not his light ariſe? <hi>Job.</hi> 25. 3. The Holy Spirit doth convince the world of ſin, becauſe they believe not on Chriſt; that is, he doth both reprove, and fault them; and not onely ſo, but convince them, and evidence to them, that this is their great ſin, and the cauſe of all other ſins, for which the wrath of God abides on them, and ſo of their covetouſneſs; and the argument whereby he thus convinceth them, it is, by glorifying Chriſt, and taking of his things, and ſhewing to them; <hi>Job.</hi> 16. 8-15. That is to ſay, to the convincing them of their ſinfulneſs, he ſhews to men, that Chriſt hath dyed for them, and is riſen again, and hath received all fulneſs, and compleatneſs into himſelf for them, that they might run unto Jeſus Chriſt with a relinquiſhing all other things, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 1-5. All things that are reproved are made manifeſt by the light; wherefore he ſaith, <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt, ariſe from the dead,</hi> (namely from dead perſons, and things, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from all filthineſs of the fleſh, and from this bitter root of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs of which the Apoſtle had been admoniſhing) <hi>and Chriſt ſhall give thee light, Eph.</hi> 5. 3-5-14.</p>
            <p>And to thoſe that turn at his reproofs, and receive the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony God hath given of his Son, he is pouring forth his ſpirit to them, and making known his words; He is giving to them the Spirit of wiſdom (to make them wiſe, to inlighten the eyes of their underſtanding) and revelation (to reveal Chriſt further to them, that they may count what hath been fore gainful to them as loſs for Chriſt; <hi>Yea, that they might ſtill count all things as loſs and dung for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt, that they may
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:52825:38"/>
win him, Phil.</hi> 3. 7-9. He is rendring his blood ſo precious before them, in ſhewing the peace thereby made, the victory thereby gotten, the righteouſneſs thereby compleated, the eternal redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereby obtained; the new Teſtament, and everlaſting cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant thereby ſealed, and confirmed, that he is thereby ſtill, and further powerfully redeeming them from their vain converſation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 18, 19. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 9. with chap. 14. 3, 4. He gives himſelf unto them, and with himſelf all things, to deliver them from this preſent evil world, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 21-23. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 4. and thus is he dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to the things here below; crucifying them to the world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 2, 3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 14. raiſing their affections to things above, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 9-12. with 3. 1, 2. ſtrengthning them to have their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation in Heaven, their minds, hearts, and affections there, and they ſet to promote the things thereof, even while they may, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the inſtructions of his grace, be exerciſed as to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man in the work of their Callings, and aſſuring them he will never forſake them, in having their converſation without covetouſneſs.</p>
            <p>2. He is alſo the great, and onely Mediator between God and Men, making interceſſion for tranſgreſſors, that they might be ſaved from their ſins, and ſo from this iniquity of their covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and come to the knowledge of the truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 4, 5. otherwiſe men that have added rebellion unto their ſin, could have no opportunity for being waſhed without which they ſhall have no part with Chriſt; but now through his daily preſenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the vertues of his ſacrifice offered once for all, patience, and forbearance is exerciſed, and ſpace of repentance vouchſafed to rebellions ones, that the Lord God may dwell amongſt them; and all this day of his patience he is vouchſafing means, and ſtretching out his hand to them that are greedy of gain, that they in hearing his words, might turn at his reproof, <hi>Pſal. 68. 18. Prov. 1. 19-23. 24. Iſa. 65. 2. Rev. 2. 20, 21. He is the Lamb of God, that taketh away</hi> (in his preſent mediation) <hi>the ſins of the world, Joh. 1. 29. and is the propitiation for the ſins of the whole world, 1 Joh.</hi> 2. 2. He is praying, <hi>Father, forgive them,</hi> as <hi>Luk. 23. 34. Lord, let it alone this year alſo, till I ſhall dig about it, and dung it, Luc.</hi> 13. 7, 8. and while he thus intercedes, the Father hears him, and it is an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table time, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 1, 2. the long-ſuffering of the Lord is, and is to be accounted ſalvation; his end herein being that men might come to repentance, and be ſaved, <hi>Iſa. 53. 10-12. 2 Pet. 3. 9. 15. Act. 14. 17. 2 Cor.</hi> 5. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:52825:38"/>And in an eſpecial manner he is mediating for thoſe that come God by him, and is therefore able to ſave them to the uttermoſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 25. without which, he were not able; he is the Mediator of the new Teſtament that by means of death for the redemption of the tranſgreſſions under the firſt Teſtament, they which are called might receive the promiſe of the eternal inheritance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 15. he is taking away, and ſo covering their ſins, that God may be patient to them, while they continue in them, that they may have ſpace vouchſafed to come to the fountain prepared, and opened, for waſhing, and cleanſing, and that the ſpirit of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and revelation in the knowledge of Chriſt may be given to them continually, that through that knowledge they might flee from the pollutions of the world; and in confeſſing their ſins, and turning to him, he is forgiving them in Heaven, and making them partakers of the forgiveneſs of their ſins, and ſo mediating the new Teſtament in his blood, that they may be cared for; to the end they may ſeek the Kingdom of God, and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; he is their Advocate (who is alſo the daily, and ſtanding propitiation for their ſins) to teach them what to pray for as they ought, and how to pray, to hear their prayers, to grant their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, and fulfil the deſires of their heart; to manage their mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to waſh, and cleanſe them in his blood, to ſubdue their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, fight their battels, ſupply their wants, and perfect what concerns them; <hi>He is a Sun, and ſheild, and will give grace, and glory; and no good thing will be withhold from them that walk upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Joh. 2. 1, 2. Pſal.</hi> 84. 11, 12.</p>
            <p>3. To this end, that thoſe that hear the word may be doers of it, and ſo take heed, and beware of covetouſneſs, he is ſetting before us the things to come at the appearing of Chriſt, and in his kingdom; and theſe are propoſed to, and ſet before men gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in the ſcriptures of truth; and of great uſefulneſs to thoſe that believe the Teſtimony of Jeſus; and are looking to the end from the beginning, to ſtrengthen them to have their converſation without carefulneſs and covetouſneſs; As to ſay</p>
            <p>1. He hath prepared a kingdom for them that receive his grace to purpoſe, even to the ſaving of their ſouls; He will raiſe them again that ſleep in Jeſus firſt, and change the ſurviving believers, and they together ſhall appear in glory, when Chriſt who is our life ſhall appear in his glory; <hi>they are now kings, and prieſts unto God, and ſhall reign on the earth,</hi> Rev. 5. 10. <hi>and 20. 4-6. the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:52825:39"/>
and dominion, and greatneſs of the kingdom under the whole heaven, ſhall be given to the people of the ſaints of the moſt high, Dan. 7. 27. they ſhall ſit with Chriſt in his throne,</hi> Rev. 3. 21. <hi>judge the world,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 2. <hi>inherit the earth,</hi> Pſal. 37. 9-11. <hi>have power over the nations, and rule them with a rod of iron,</hi> Rev. 2. 26, 27. and then compleatly bear the Image of the Heavenly in their bodies, which ſhall be faſhioned into the likeneſs of his glorious body; In their ſpirits, injoying the harveſt of all bleſſing, of which they have now but a firſt fruits. In that dominion, and rule that ſhall be given them when he ſhall make new heavens, and a new earth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 49. in being Chriſt's they are <hi>Abraham's ſeed, and heires according to promiſe, and ſo heyres of the world to come,</hi> Rom. 4. 13. Heb. 2. 5. and ſhall injoy the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> which was given to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his ſeed by an everlaſting covenant; the which he hath not yet poſſeſſed; <hi>God gave him none inheritance in it, no not ſo much as to ſet his foot on, yet he promiſed he would give it to him for a poſſeſſion, and to his ſeed after him,</hi> Act. 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. and faithful is he that hath promiſed, who alſo will do it; This everlaſting cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant being confirmed by the blood of Jeſus, who is brought again from the dead, and alive for evermore, being the great ſhepherd of the ſheep, and Mediator of the new Teſtament—that the called may recieve the promiſe of the eternal inheritance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 14. and 13. 20. and bleſſed is he that believeth; for there ſhall be a performance of the things that are ſpoken. Chriſt himſelf as raiſed from the dead, being the foundation and ground of it; and he as given to us in the Goſpel, and by faith received is that in which God makes with us, and gives us aſſureance of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting covenant, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 3. with <hi>Act.</hi> 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4.</p>
            <p>Now this bleſſed hope which is declared to us in the word of the truth of the Goſpel, is very powerful, as viewed in the Croſs of Chriſt, to deliver us from this preſent evil world; we are ſaved by hope from our ſins, and ſo from loving, and luſting after this World. Hence frequently the Holy Ghoſt ſets this before us, to take off our hearts from the things here below, and that we might be without carefulneſs, and covetouſneſs. Thus our Savior in this <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. takes occaſion from the miſcarriages of this man who deſired him to ſpeak to his brother to divide the inheritance with him, to warn his diſciples of taking thought for their life what they ſhall eat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to ſeal home that admonition, ſaith; <hi>Feare not little flock, For it is your Fathers good pleaſure to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:52825:39"/>
give you the kingdom,</hi> (therefore) <hi>ſell that you have and give almes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 22-32-35. ſo the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>When Chriſt our life ſhall appear, then ſhall ye alſo appear with him in glory; Mortifie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your members that are upon the earth</hi>—covetouſneſs <hi>which is idolatry;</hi> Col. 3. 4, 5. He that hath his hope in Chriſt, that when he ſhall appear we ſhall be like him, &amp;c. purifieth himſelf as he is pure. As Chriſt is pure in his work, waſhing, and cleanſing from deſires of being now manifeſted, and from minding, and affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things of the world, ſo ſuch an one purifieth himſelf, daily, and continually he goes on ſo to do, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 1-3. how forcible was this bleſſed hope with the holy men in former times, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem them from the earth,; they ſaw the promiſes afar off, and were perſwaded of them, and embraced them (kiſſed, and cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them, as very deſireable, and lovely) and (as the effect, and conſequent thereof) confeſſed <hi>that they were ſtrangers, and pilgrims on the earth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Heb. 11. 13. 16. And by faith Moſes preferred the reproach of Chriſt before the treaſures of Egypt, and refuſed to be called the ſon of</hi> Pharaohs <hi>daughter; For he had reſpect to the recompence of reward,</hi> Heb. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24-26. and if this had ſuch efficacy on them, when they ſaw the promiſes afar off, would it not now rather crucifie us to the world, and the World to us, were we looking to thoſe things not ſeen? conſidering, that the promiſe God made to the Fathers he hath fulfilled, <hi>in that he hath raiſed Chriſt from the dead, in whom all the promiſes of God are yea, &amp; amen,</hi> Act. 13. 32, 33. 2 Cor. 1. 20. would it not make us willing to go forth unto him without the camp, bearing his reproach; <hi>For we have here no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing City, but</hi> (have good reaſon to) <hi>ſeek one to come,</hi> Heb. 13. 13, 14. Yea and eſpecially now the grace of God doth inſtruct, and move us to have our converſation without covetouſneſs, <hi>For the end of all things is at hand,</hi> 1 Pet 4. 7. <hi>the time is ſhort, it remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that both they that have wives be as if they bad none,</hi> (as with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to covetouſneſs, and carefulneſs, in laying up for themſelves, and theirs here on earth) <hi>and they that weep</hi> (for any loſs, depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, or diſappointment in God's providences ordered to them) <hi>as though they wept not; and they that rejoyce</hi> (for any gain advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, or increaſe) <hi>as though they rejoyced not; and they that buy</hi> (that they may have ſome viſible maintenance ſecured to them) <hi>as though they poſſeſſed not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For the faſhion of this world paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> 1 Cor. 7. 29-32. <hi>Wherefore gird we up the loynes of our mind</hi> (from wandring in our deſires after the things on the earth, or
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:52825:40"/>
ſetting our hearts upon them) <hi>be ſober, and hope to the end, for the grace that is to be brought at the revelation of Jeſus Chriſt; For yet a little while, and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry, now the juſt ſhall live by faith,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 13. Heb. 10. 37. 38<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2 Per. 3. 11-14.</p>
            <p>2. And that we may take heed, and beware of covetouſneſs, conſider the terror of the Lord, againſt thoſe that continue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as declared in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>The Lord will be terrible unto them, ſuch as ſuch ſhall not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdom of God; <hi>let no man deceive us with vain words; for becauſe of this the wrath of God cometh continually upon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of diſobedience to the glorious Goſpel which comes to redeem and deliver from the earth, and from having fellowſhip with men in this unfruitful work,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 10, 11. Eph. 5. 5-7. Col. 3. 5, 6. <hi>The day of the Lord will come as a ſnare on all them that dwell on the face of the whole earth, Luk.</hi> 21. 34, 35. The Lord will be very terrible to ſuch in that day of wrath; <hi>in that day ſhall a man caſt his idols of ſilver, and his idols of gold, which they made each one for himſelf, to worſhip to the Moles, and to the Batts, to go into the clefts of the rocks, and into the tops of the ragged rocks, for fear of the Lord, and for the glory of his Majeſty, when he ariſeth to ſhake terribly the earth,</hi> Iſa. 2. 16. 21. Oh let us not by following lying vanities forſake our own mercies; <hi>what will it profit a man to gain the whole world, and looſe his own ſoul?</hi> theſe are idolaters, and as ſuch they ſhall be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, their worm dyeth not, in that lake into which they ſhall be caſt, and their fire is not quenched. Were it not infinitely better for us now to receive the love of the truth that we may be ſaved from our iniquities, and idols, than expoſe our ſelves to the wrath to come? Oh who knoweth the power of it? <hi>what ſhall a man then give in exchange for his ſoul?</hi> than a great ranſome cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver; <hi>will he eſteem thy riches, no not gold, nor all the forces of ſtrength;</hi> Job. 36. 18, 19. theſe profit not in a day of wrath. Oh how dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful will it then be, when the Son of man ſhall ſay, <hi>Depart ye curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into everlaſting fire, propared for the Devil, and his angels? For I was an hungred, and ye gave me no meat; I was thirſty, and ye gave me no drink; I was a ſtranger, and ye took me not in; naked, and ye cloathed me not; ſick, and in priſon, and ye viſited me not,</hi> Math. 25. 41-43. He ſaith not, your heart was ſo given to your covetouſneſs, you ſo loved the world, and the things thereof, that you defrauded me, and took away from me wrongfully what was mine; you were not content with that portion of earthly things that was in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:52825:40"/>
your own poſſeſſion, but you coveted mine, and took it away by violence, and extortion, and ſo expoſed me to hunger, thirſt, cold, and nakedneſs; no, this was not directly laid to their charge, though this is ſtrongly ſuppoſed to be a more grievous iniquity; but that for which they are ſentenced to everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, it is, that they did not caſt their bread upon the waters; they withheld more than was meet, and now it tends to this great poverty; they are now left deſtitute of his favour, and for ever ſeparated from him, and doomed to the vengeance of eternal fire; now when his poor ſervants that formerly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed their evil things are comforted, thoſe who formerly injoyed their good things are tormented, and ſhall be ſo for ever; For there will then be ſuch a great gulf fixed, that there is no paſſing from that ſtate and condition to another, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 25. at this our heart may tremble, and be moved out of place; who amongſt us will give ear to this? who will hearken, and hear for the time to come? ſuch an one as thus ſhuts up the bowels of his compaſſion when opened, may poſſibly by ſome men be look't upon as an hard man, and as one that too much loves his money, and this may be deemed as a venial, or ſmall offence in him; and yet he may paſs for an honeſt man, though ſomewhat hard; but were it wiſely conſidered, how ſuch wil hereafter be proceeded againſt, it would, as viewed in Chriſt (in whom there is now forgiveneſs, and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and power to deliver from the wrath to come) be powerful to awaken us to quit our ſelves from this iniquity.</p>
            <p>What hath been ſaid, in ſhewing that we may take heed, and beware of covetouſneſs, and by what means we may do it, may be of uſefulneſs to us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1. To ſhew unto us the preciouſneſs of the blood of Chriſt, in its vertue, and in it's diſcovery for redeeming us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 18, 19. As that is it whereby forgiveneſs is procured, peace made, ſpirit received, great and precious promiſes confirmed, eternal life, and redemption obtained; ſo the diſcovery, and application thereof is that whereby he doth waſh us from our ſins, <hi>Rev. 1. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1 Joh.</hi> 1. 7. redeem us unto God from the Earth, and from amongſt men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 9. and 14. 4, 5. purges from dead works, as well as from thoſe that are deadly, to ſerve the living God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 14.</p>
            <p>2. It ſhews unto us the reaſon why we are not waſhed from this filthineſs of covetouſneſs, namely, becauſe we come not unto, and are not obedient to the blood of ſprinkling, 1 <hi>Pet. 1. 2. Eph.</hi> 5. 6.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:52825:41"/>
for were we obedient thereto, it would ſave us; and if we do not thus experiment it, let us judge our ſelves, and ſearch, and try our ways, for certainly we have been wandring out of the way of underſtanding, 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 2. 1 Theſ. 1. 9, 10. Oh thou who art named the houſe of Jacob is the ſpirit of the Lord ſtraitned? are theſe his doings? do not my words do good to him that walketh uprightly? Mica.</hi> 2. 2-7.</p>
            <p>3. Let it inſtruct and ingage us to give more earneſt heed to the things which God hath teſtified of his Son: in what he hath done, and is become: in what he is now doing: and in what he will do, and ſo let us receive, and walk in the ſpirit, minding the things of the ſpirit, and we ſhall not fulfil the luſts of the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 16. this is our victory, even our faith; who is he that overcometh the world, but he that believeth that Jeſus is the Son of God? 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 4, 5. it is onely through the ſpirit we may mortify the deeds of the body, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13. it is good for us to know, <hi>that a man is not juſtified by the works of the law, but by the faith of Chriſt</hi> (the word of faith, in which he is now manifeſted to be the foundation, and object of faith, as formerly he was not) that we may believe in Jeſus Chriſt, that we may be juſtifyed, (and cleanſed alſo, as ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified ſometimes ſignifies; as <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. 14.) by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the works of the law; <hi>for by the works of the law ſhall no fleſh be juſtified, Gal.</hi> 2. 16. That we may therefore flee covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, conſider we, and remember what God hath given us in Chriſt, and the hope ſet before us, to be poſſeſſed, and injoyed when he ſhall appear in glory, and wait through the ſpirit (who glorifies Chriſt) for the hope of Gods righteouſneſs through faith; ſo ſhall we meet with his Divine power for delivering us from every path of the deſtroyer, <hi>Col. 3. 3-5. Gal.</hi> 5. 5. And to ingage us to take heed, and beware of covetouſneſs, let us briefly conſider the motive here laid down by our Savior, to ſeal home this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>For a man's life conſiſts not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth;</hi> From whence we noted</p>
            <p>3. That the conſideration of this, that a man's life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth, is alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as viewed in the glorious Goſpel to move us to receive this admonition, <hi>viz.</hi> to take heed, and beware of covetouſneſs.</p>
            <p>By [<hi>the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth</hi>] is here meant, the things of this preſent world, as appears, in that it is ſaid, <hi>a man,</hi> as a man, poſſeſſeth them; and by the parable which our
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:52825:41"/>
Savior preſently joyns unto this Caveat, <hi>Luk. 12. 16-18. the things of the Earth, &amp; which he poſſeſſeth here on Earth,</hi> as diſtinguiſhed from what is laid up in Heaven, in the motions, and teaching of his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> grace.</p>
            <p>And by [<hi>a man's life</hi>] is meant, that life which he hath as a man, or which is proper to him as a man, as diſtinguiſhed from that life which God hath prepared for men, and given them in Chriſt; <hi>this is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, that God hath given to us</hi> (mankind) <hi>eternal life; and this life is in his Son, 1 Joh.</hi> 5. 10, 11. and which life he is giving with Chriſt; ſo as in finding him we ſhall find, and be made partakers of it; in which is contained the forgiveneſs of our ſins, and the favor of God, and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with him; which is now given through the knowledge of him; our Savior here ſpeaks not of this life, nor is this man's life as a man, or Son of <hi>Adam,</hi> but obtained, and treaſured up for us in the ſecond Man, the laſt <hi>Adam;</hi> this is called <hi>the life of God, Eph.</hi> 4. 18. which he hath given us in, and is giving us with his Son, and making him par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of it by faith that receiveth him; had our Savior ſaid, <hi>eternal life,</hi> or <hi>the life of God conſiſts not herein,</hi> many would have been ready to ſay, they know that well enough, who yet are given to covetouſneſs, and ſo are idolaters, and rejoyce, and truſt in theſe things, as if eternal life conſiſted in them; But here he deſcends ſo low, in aſſerting the emptineſs, &amp; unprofitableneſs of man's abundance, as that he may ſhew that the thoughts of man, yea and of the wiſe alſo are very vain.</p>
            <p>For what man is there that doth not ſecretly think that his life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the abundance of the things which he injoyeth; but it is not ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his life, his natural life which is given to him through the Mediator, and which God doth preſerve during his pleaſure by his bleſſing of meat, and drink to him (<hi>for man lives not by bread alone, but by every word that proceeds out of his mouth,</hi>) and by his gracious protection, this conſiſts not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth. That is</p>
            <p>1. As life, and to live, ſignifies in Scripture, a comfortable being, and injoying chearfulneſs, and gladneſs (as 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. 6. ſo in an higher ſenſe the word is uſed, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 8. ſo a man's life conſiſts not therein; a man lives never a whit the more merrily; this is that which men (at leaſt) think to be in abundance; they think it will make their lives comfortable; they propoſe to themſelves a great deal of contentment in having an abundance, and therefore they deſire, and luſt after it, and labor to be rich in themſelves, and they ſay, or will ſay, <hi>Eat, drink, and be merry,</hi> as he in the parable, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 19. but they never come at it; it makes not their preſent life comfortable, and joyous. For</p>
            <p>1. There is no ſatisfaction in theſe things; <hi>he that loveth ſilver ſhall not be ſatisfied with ſilver; nor he that loves abundance with increaſe, Eccl.</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:52825:42"/>
5. 10. the appetite, or deſire, is not filled; but he ſtill cryes, <hi>Give, give; he coveteth greedily all the day long, Eccl. 6. 7. Pro.</hi> 21. 26. and ſo is like the troubled ſea that cannot reſt; ſurely every man walks in a vain ſhew, ſurely they are diſquietedin vain; he heapeth up (continually, &amp;c) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. 9. while they ſeek for reſt in theſe things, their deſire is inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged as Hell; and they cannot be ſatisfied; this is not our reſt, becauſe it is polluted, it is not bread, and therefore it will not ſatisfie, <hi>Iſa. 55. 2. Mica.</hi> 2. 10. Chriſt onely is the reſt where the weary may find reſt; but the abundance of theſe things give no reſt, and ſo the life cannot be comfortable: he is ſtill wiſhing for, and deſiring more; and ſuch is the way of every one that is greedy of gain, that it takes away the life (the comfort of the life) of the owners thereof, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 19. and from the greedineſs of gain they are led to much ſore travel, and labor, that they may increaſe to themſelves, and more load themſelves with thick clay; it is a loading themſelves indeed, for it is an heavy burden to them, fills them with trouble, grief, and much diſquietment, and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpirit, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 6. yea, though at ſome time they may laugh, and rejoyce, yet it is but as the crackling of thorns under a pot, appears great, but it is preſently gone; <hi>yea in laughter the heart may be ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and the end of that mirth is heavineſs; Eccl.</hi> 2. 2. and 7. 6. <hi>Pro.</hi> 14. 13. it is the word of Chriſt kept in the midſt of the heart that is life to thoſe that find it, and health to all their fleſh; and though all the days of the affliction of ſuch is evil; <hi>yet he that is of a merry heart, hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual feaſt, Pro.</hi> 4. 20-22. and 15. 15. <hi>he then that will love life, and ſee good days</hi> (live chearfully, and comfortably;) <hi>let him</hi> (not labor to be rich, but) <hi>refrain his tongue from evil, and his lips that they ſpeak no guile; let him eſchew evil, and do good, let him ſeek peace, and enſue it, 1 Pet.</hi> 3. 10, 11.</p>
            <p>2. As ſuch an ones life, or living comfortably conſiſts not in his abundance; becauſe while he ſeeks reſt therein, he ſtill deſires after, and labors for more, and ſo diſquiets himſelf in vain: ſo alſo he meets with much vexation in bethinking how to ſecure to himſelf what he hath gotten, like this rich man in the parable, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 17, 18. he thought within himſelf, ſaying, <hi>What ſhall I do, becauſe I have no room where to beſtow my fruits? and he ſaid, this will I do, I will pull down my barns, and build greater,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>All his days are ſorrows, and his travel grief; Yea his heart taketh no reſt in the night,</hi> Eccl 2. 23. <hi>The ſleep of a laboring man is ſweet, whether he eat little, or much; but the abundance of the rich will not ſuffer him to ſleep, Eccl.</hi> 5. 12. they are now caring how they ſhall lay up what they have, ſo as to ſecure it; or how they may let it out, or l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y it out ſafely, or to greateſt advantage; and full of fears, leſt thieves
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:52825:42"/>
ſhould break through, and ſteal; or leſt thoſe in whoſe hands they have diſpoſed it ſhould be impoveriſhed, and break, and they looſe all; or when troubles are in the Earth, and God orders judgements of war, and ſword, leſt all ſhould be taken away by violence from them; all his days he eateth in darkneſs, and affliction; many ſorrows, cares, and feares attend the abundance here poſſeſſed, and injoyed; and ſo a man's life, the comfort of it, conſiſts not herein, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5. 14-17.</p>
            <p>3. Yea, God diſtributeth ſorrows alſo, and is ordering ſorrow, and wrath to them with their ſickneſs, while they poſſeſs their abundance, and are not laying it up in Heaven according to the inſtructions of his grace, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5, 14-17. and this to a gracious end, while called to day, that they might ſeek after that treaſure hid in Chriſt, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs. To the ſinner (to thoſe that erre, and miſs the way, wander out of the way of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and ſo miſs the mark) he giveth travel, to gather, and to heap up, <hi>&amp;c. Eccl.</hi> 2. 26.</p>
            <p>2. And as by man's life may be meant the preſervation, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of it, ſo it conſiſts not in the abundance of the things which he poſſeſſeth; this will not prolong his days upon the Earth; Yea, on the contrary, as the Proverb ſaith, <hi>He that hateth covetouſneſs ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long his days, Prov. 28. 16. which of you</hi> (ſaith our Savior) <hi>by taking thought, can add one cubit to his ſtature,</hi> or age? <hi>Math.</hi> 6. 27. Yea many times ſuch ſhorten their lives, and dye before their time. Sometimes more directly, as the fruit of their delighting in their abundance, in ſeeking to add to what they have by their labors, cares, and breaking their reſt, and ſleep, and adventuring themſelves into danger when an advantage is put into their hands for increaſing to themſelves, and that they make ſure their uncertain riches, and by many fears occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to them they bring themſelves to untimely ends, and ſhorten their days; <hi>ſuch is the way of every one that is greedy of gains, which taketh away the life of the owners thereof, Prov.</hi> 1. 19. and however God is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked, when men harden their hearts againſt his grace, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs of inſtruction, ſometimes to order, and permit violent perſons to take away their lives, and they dye unlamented, as it was with <hi>Jeh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iakim, Jer.</hi> 22. 17-19. or himſelf to take them away by ſickneſs, and wrath with ſickneſs ordered to them, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5. 17. and their abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance will not remove his hand from off them, though they have been truſting in their abundance, and pleaſing themſelves that they can procure ſuch means, and Phyſicians as may recover them; yet if he will not withdraw his hand, the proud helpers muſt ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him; behold he taketh away, who can hinder him? who will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:52825:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
him what doeſt thou? then neither their gold, nor their ſilver ſhall be able to deliver them; <hi>he is a God that reſpecteth not perſons, nor taketh reward, Job. 9. 12, 13. Deut. 10. 17. Ezek.</hi> 7. 19. or he may take them away ſuddenly, and deprive them of opportunity of ſeeking help any where; as it was with this rich man; <hi>Thou fool, this night thy ſoul ſhall be taken away from thee;</hi> he accepts not the perſons of Princes, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards the rich (who have abundance in their poſſeſſion) more than the poor; for they are all the work of his hands: in a moment ſhall they dye, and the people ſhall be troubled at midnight, and paſs away, and the mighty ſhall be taken away without hand, <hi>Job.</hi> 34. 19, 20.</p>
            <p>Oh that it might be then of this uſe to us, to take heed and beware of covetouſneſs; ſeeing neither the comfort, nor continuance of a mans life conſiſteth in poſſeſſing of an abundance; and if it be not able to do that which is the leaſt, and that which every one propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to himſelf in deſiring, and laboring for it, how then can it do what is greateſt? if a man's life conſiſts not herein, ſurely much leſs doth eternal life conſiſt herein: <hi>Oh then let us not labor for this meat that periſheth, but for that which indureth to eternal life, which the Son of of man will give unto us, for him hath God the Father ſealed.</hi> Let us not ſeek what we ſhall eat, or what we ſhall drink, neither let us be of doubtful mind; For all theſe things do the nations of the world ſeek after, and our Father knoweth we have need of theſe things; but let us rather <hi>ſeek the Kingdom of God, and all theſe things ſhall be added to us;</hi> And that we may have our converſation without covetouſneſs, and carefulneſs, and caſt our cares upon him, oh let us feed upon the fleſh of Chriſt, as given for the life of the world, this will ſtrengthen thereto.</p>
            <p>Remember, and conſider his infinite love in appointing him by his grace to taſte death for every man, and the preciouſneſs of his blood, in the vertue whereof he is raiſed, and glorified; this we ſhall find powerful to ingage, and ſtrengthen us to ſeek thoſe things above, to ſet our affections on things above, not on things on the Earth; and ſo to diſpoſe our way, that God in all things may be glorified through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be praiſe, and dominion for ever, and ever,</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
